<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The universal Christian doctrine of the Day of Judgment applied to the doctrine of the thousand years kingdom of Christ (herein guided by Mr. Baxter's Reply) to vindicate it from all objections ... / by Thomas Beverley ...</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2186</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5659</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13085371</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13085371</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97298</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27634)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97298)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 408:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The universal Christian doctrine of the Day of Judgment applied to the doctrine of the thousand years kingdom of Christ (herein guided by Mr. Baxter's Reply) to vindicate it from all objections ... / by Thomas Beverley ...</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>"A postscript to the reader": p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Reply to Mr. Tho. Beverley's Answer to my reasons.</term>
               <term>Judgment Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97298:1"/>
            <p>THE UNIVERSAL Chriſtian Doctrine OF THE <hi>Day of Iudgment:</hi> Applied to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Thouſand Years Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi> (Herein Guided by Mr. <hi>BAXTER</hi>'s Reply) To Vindicate It from all Objections. Shewing as is the One, ſo is the Other; <hi>(VIZ.)</hi> His Judging the <hi>Quick</hi> and the <hi>Dead;</hi> and His Appearing, and His Kingdom. Which, ſeeing it muſt have ſome Duration, the Scripture 1000 Years, is on Great Proof <hi>Preferr'd</hi> By <hi>THOMAS BEVERLEY,</hi> An humble Miniſter of that Kingdom.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>II. PET. III. 7, 8.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>—The Day of Judgment, and of the Perdition of ungodly men. But Beloved, be not ignorant of this</hi> One Thing, <hi>That one Day is with the Lord as a Tbouſand Years,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97298:2"/>
            <head>The Preface TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe Many will Deign to Read a <hi>Preface,</hi> that will not a <hi>Book;</hi> I ſhall take Freedom to give a Proſpect of the <hi>Whole</hi> in a <hi>Preface:</hi> And firſt, I am very Senſible my <hi>Lot</hi> of <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> is fallen on ſuch <hi>Ground,</hi> that each <hi>Point</hi> muſt be Disputed for; not A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn'd, nor Simply Taught; but Argued, and Won, as it were by Inches; And which much Increaſes the <hi>Difficulty,</hi> The <hi>Land of Promiſe,</hi> as the <hi>Map</hi> of it lies in Scripture, is not in any Entire <hi>Table,</hi> but in ſeveral ſmaller <hi>Lines</hi> variouſly Planted, which muſt be Transplanted and laid Together.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Who is Sufficient for ſuch a Thing,</hi> as a <hi>Teacher?</hi> And as for <hi>Hearers,</hi> They are not only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nteachable, or <hi>Dull of Hearing,</hi> but are Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd, and Cry out againſt this <hi>Heritage of the Lord,</hi> as a <hi>Speckled Bird:</hi> Some call ſuch a <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> Whimſie, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nintelligible Non-ſenſe, Fooliſhneſs; To other Graver Chriſtians, and even <hi>Teachers:</hi> It is a <hi>Scandal,</hi> an <hi>Offence,</hi> full of Cauſes of Objection; And even to many more Favourable, unintelligible <hi>Myſtery;</hi> Plain Things, ſay they, are more Profitable: But none of theſe Things move Me, that I ſhould not <hi>Take heed to Fulfil this Miniſtery,</hi> I have <hi>Received of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I intend this <hi>Small Tract,</hi> not ſo much as a <hi>Rejoynder</hi> to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Reply</hi> upon my <hi>Anſwer;</hi> For, who am I, that I ſhould maintain a <hi>Controverſie</hi> with ſo <hi>Honoured, Able,</hi> and <hi>Faithful a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> I only with Thankfulneſs take Advice from Him, what <hi>Points</hi> to Clear, what to Guard, what Advantage to take for Defence; And had I not found ſome Arugments, which I have not propos'd, or not fully urg'd before; and ſo fit a <hi>Medium</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument</hi> of <hi>Conveyance</hi> of this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as the <hi>Parallel</hi> between it, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally receiv'd <hi>Article of Faith; Chriſt's coming to Judge the Quick and the Dead at his Kingdom;</hi> (which muſt needs be a <hi>middle Kingdom,)</hi> I had been ſilent; Nor ſhall I think of opening my Mouth any further in this <hi>Point,</hi> till I find ſomething Objected; which, what I have now ſaid, if Duly Conſider'd, will not Anſwer, which, I am much in hope cannot be; For to be Conſcious to have ſaid, what can be ſpoken by One, even as an Oath, ought to conclude One, and on
<pb facs="tcp:97298:2"/> Ones own part to be an <hi>End of All Strife;</hi> Of ſmall Queſtions and Exceptions, I know there is no End: And <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs with Thanksgiving to God, and with Subordinate Thankfulneſs to Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> On His ſo often Naming a <hi>Middle Kingdom</hi> by way of Objection, it was as it were by a Divine Prompting ſaid to me; This Notion of a <hi>Middle Kingdom,</hi> which the <hi>Day of Judgment</hi> must needs be, and which I have long ſince underſtood the ſame with the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> is the Key of this <hi>Great Myſtery;</hi> and ſo I have Found it, and am ſo Fully ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it; Even above, all I have written before; that I am at perfect Peace, and will Contend no more; I can look on any further Objection, but as the Talk of Looſers: For I am ſure, ſuch an <hi>Appearance</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Day of Judgment</hi> is, or ſuch a <hi>Return with the Kingdom Receiv'd,</hi> as <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 15. or a <hi>Coming</hi> not [into] as is to Loſs, Tranſlated, <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. 43. but according to all Scripture Language [in his <hi>Kingdom]</hi> muſt needs be in the <hi>Middle</hi> between the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> hitherto, and to <hi>Eternity;</hi> And it muſt have a Space of duration defined, for It is not <hi>Eternal,</hi> All Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; I therefore preferr only the Scriptures naming a 1000 Years, with ſuch Apparences of that Time, and according to the ſo Known <hi>Axiom</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the People of God before the New Teſtament; The <hi>Day of Judgment ſhall be a</hi> 1000 <hi>Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is evident alſo from the <hi>Article</hi> Founded on 2 Tim. 4 1. Chriſt <hi>Judges the Quick,</hi> or <hi>Living,</hi> even as the <hi>Dead</hi> at his Appearing and Kingdom, There must be <hi>Saints Rais'd,</hi> and <hi>Saints, The Living, The Remaining,</hi> of which I Treat according to Scripture Guidance, as by 1 Theſſ. 4. 17.</p>
            <p>The <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> muſt needs be at the ſame Time New, by ſuch a Luſtre of Chriſt's <hi>Appearance,</hi> the <hi>Sun of Rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teouſneſs;</hi> Even as the <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> are, as it were, New to us every Summer by the Suns Return; And it is no more, then Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> intended in his Firſt Creation, ſuch a Glory of it: And I cannot but Give, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 45. 18. in ſomewhat a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tranſlation, but ſuch as I ſuppoſe the Original will well Bear, to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; upon naming the <hi>Salvation of Iſrael</hi> as an <hi>Everlaſting Salvation, World without end;</hi> It follows, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> that <hi>Created the Heavens,</hi> that <hi>Formed the Earth; He hath Eſtabliſhed it, He Created it,</hi> not (ſaith the Tranſlation [in vain] ſay I out of the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> for a <hi>[Tohu]</hi> ſuch an Inanity of Glory, as It is now; <hi>He Formed it,</hi> [to be Inhabited] ſaith the Tranſlation; ſay I, according to the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> [for the <hi>Sabbath]</hi> even this Great <hi>Sabbatiſm,</hi> wherein <hi>Jehovah ſhall be one,</hi> his <hi>Name one,</hi> none elſe, no <hi>Idols Name any more for ever.</hi> And then ſhall He Appear that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Foreknower, <hi>declaring the End</hi> from the <hi>Beginning,</hi> that <hi>He may be known to be God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by All Theſe Things, I hope Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> will be ſatisfied concerning the <hi>Specificneſs</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> Beginning with a <hi>Judgment,</hi> and ending with a <hi>Judgment,</hi> and its entire middle Space, an Appearance according to that <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, viz.</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> in the Glory of the <hi>Reſtitution of All Things</hi> by the <hi>Second Adam,</hi> the Redeemer, the Reſtorer of all the Ruins of the <hi>Firſt Adam;</hi> and an Appearance of the <hi>Wicked</hi> in <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Contempt;</hi> and both theſe for the 1000 Y. <hi>Receiving</hi> what they <hi>have done,</hi> in <hi>Body</hi> before the <hi>Tribunal of Chriſt;</hi> Now All will Acknowledge as this Kingdom hath not been yet; So it
<pb facs="tcp:97298:3"/> ſhall not be for ever, but be <hi>deliver'd up;</hi> Here therefore is a perfect <hi>Specificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> except <hi>Specification</hi> be an unknown <hi>School-Term.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Know in ſome Things, I differ from that Sweet, as well as moſt Judicious, and Pious Writer Mr. <hi>Increaſe Mather,</hi> as Appears by his Accurate diſcourſe; <hi>De Signo Filii Hominis,</hi> or of the <hi>Sign of the Son of Man.</hi> I ſhould be moſt Glad by Friendlieſt Conference, or entercourſe of Letters to conciliate; as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a <hi>Scripture-Line of Time</hi> to this State, concerning Chriſt having his Palace of Glory, not on this <hi>New Earth,</hi> but in the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> concerning the <hi>Wicked Dead Rais'd;</hi> In which Points I perceive my Self to differ from Him, but as I Hope on Great Scripture Grounds.</p>
            <p>Now to Conclude All; This <hi>Kingdom</hi> is the Great Practical Doctrine, which, when It ſhall be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally <hi>Preach'd</hi> by the <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> ſhall Bring in all the World, <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> to Christ; And beſides the Bleſſed Effuſions of the Spirit, that ſhall go along with it, How muſt it needs in Reaſon prevail! For what would the Great Value and purchaſe of, but a 100 Years in the Vigors, and All Affluences of Life be, and in ſuch a <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> as are now, and if Men were ſo enclin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d, in all wiſe, and vertuous Converſes?</p>
            <p>Of what Ineſtimable Value then to every ſerious Conſiderer, even now, the offer of ſo much a Higher, and Longer 1000 Y. of Life, as is propos'd on ſo Great Scripture Grounds? How may it ſatisfie that Appetite, Implanted by Creation into our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which is that very <hi>Olam,</hi> or <hi>World ſet by God in the Heart of Man. Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ.</hi> 3 11. the Deſire to ſee the Glory of God in his Viſibly Glorious Creation, for a perfect Duration of Time?</p>
            <p>But how much ſtronger will the Impreſſion be upon an Enlightned, Convinced, Awaken'd World under that <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel Preach'd?</hi> when that ſhall be Fully declar'd, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>liev'd, that Few will now Believe, though it be never ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Told Them; In the mean Time, ſeeing we All profeſs to Believe Fully the Apoſtle <hi>Peter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Looking</hi> for <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth according to his Promiſe,</hi> wherein <hi>Righteouſneſs ſhall dwell.</hi> Let us Reſolve what <hi>Manner of Perſons we ought to be in all</hi> that <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of Converſation; and let us <hi>Grow in Grace,</hi> and the <hi>Knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> beyond the <hi>Beginnings</hi> of his <hi>Doctrine, Going on to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> and ſo unravel the <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> where it Began in not ſo doing; and above all, Let us <hi>Give All Dilligence,</hi> that we may be <hi>Found of him in Peace without S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot,</hi> and <hi>Blameleſs,</hi> and by Him be ſo <hi>Preſented before the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let us conſider, the <hi>Day</hi> is <hi>near Approaching;</hi> Concerning the Truth of which, I make Appeal to Him, to ſhow by his <hi>Arm made bare</hi> in unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Evidence of Fact, and Event, every Thing in its proper Time; And I am now waiting at this Time, when the <hi>Kings</hi> are preparing to <hi>Go out to War</hi> for a <hi>Dawn</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Morning Star</hi> on the <hi>Suffering Witneſſes</hi> of the yet Afflicted <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Vaudois;</hi> and that the <hi>Rod of Iron</hi> ſhould begin to Break t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at <hi>Potters Veſſel,</hi> whom patience hath yet ſpar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d from being a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (for what ends will be ſeen,) who with a more then <hi>Herodian</hi> Inſolence, and Cruelty, hath n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> only let Reſt on Him, as <hi>Herod,</hi> but even Hunted for ſuch Attributions, as to a <hi>God,</hi> and not to a <hi>Man,</hi> and ſo Inhumanely <hi>Vex'd</hi> ſo many of the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> to pleaſe a <hi>Sacrilegiouſly Flattering Jeſuitic</hi> Order. <hi>Now to the only wiſe God be Glory for ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97298:3"/>
            <head>A REPRESENTATION OF THE Thouſand Years Kingdom OF CHRIST, <hi>Endeavouring to Reconcile it to the General</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions <hi>of the Faith of</hi> Chriſtians; <hi>and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the Judgment of the Eminent Servants, and Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, with a Vindication from Further Objections.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Can Sincerely Appeal to the Searcher of Hearts, I am in all the Subſtantial, and Eſſential Points of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> of the Judgment of all the Wiſeſt, Soundeſt, and moſt Univerſally Approved Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, and Chriſtians, in the Faith at once <hi>Deliver'd to the Saints,</hi> and have no By, nor Secret Opinions in Reſerve, either concerning the Perſon of the Great Media or, God and Man, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dom, as if it had not been from the Beginning, or were not to be for ever in ſuch Explications of it, as the Churches of Chriſt moſt Agree in according to Scripture.</p>
            <p>I make the ſame Appeal conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rning my Belief of the Eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aints, with, and by Chriſt in the Diſtinctneſs of Humane nature, <hi>Spirits</hi> in Bodies of Glory, united by Him to the Father, and yet each one in his own proper Perſonality, and ſo made Truly Equal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Elect Angels;</hi> and of the puniſhment of the wicked in their Spirits, and Bodies together with the <hi>Devil</hi> and his <hi>Angels,</hi> even through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97298:4"/> a Strict and proper Eternity <hi>a Parte Poſt,</hi> as They ſpeak, or for ever.</p>
            <p>Except therefore my Doctrine, and Affirmation of the Kingdom of the Thouſand Years, can be ſhown<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in a perfect Amity and Conciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with this <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Form of Sound Words;</hi> I Acknowledge It ought to be Rejected; I therefore Attempt in very Brief, to ſhew it to be in ſuch a State of Agreement, and to vindicate it from Exceptions to it.</p>
            <p>I obſerve therefore one Great Complex of Articles of Faith, wherein All Chriſtians are, as much, as in any Point of Chriſtianity at One; and They may be thus Given:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there ſhall be a <hi>Day</hi> or Time before the State and Kingdom of Eternity; wherein Jeſus Chriſt ſhall <hi>Come from the Right Hand of the Father</hi> to <hi>Judge the World,</hi> and this, as <hi>Man, Acts</hi> 17. 31.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Jeſus Chriſt ſhall <hi>Come</hi> in the <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Power of the Father</hi> to this <hi>Judgment,</hi> and that It ſhall be a moſt Illuſtrious <hi>Appearance</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that was not before, nor ſhall be after. For <hi>He comes in his Kingdom;</hi> and the <hi>King ſhall ſay, &amp;c. Matth.</hi> 25. and He <hi>Sits on the Throne of his Glory. v.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>v.</hi> 34.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That at the ſame Time, There ſhall be a Glorious Reſurrection, and Appearance of his <hi>Saints</hi> with Him; as Sharers in the Glories, and Triumphs of that <hi>Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Saints, that ſhall at that Time be living, and Rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Earth; ſhall not <hi>Dye,</hi> but at the very ſame Time be <hi>Chang'd</hi> ſo, as that They alſo may <hi>have their part</hi> in the ſame <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That there ſhall be a <hi>Reſurrection of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njust,</hi> and of <hi>Thoſe that have done Evil</hi> to the <hi>Condemnation</hi> to the Diſhonour and Contempt, and to the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> that ſhall at that <hi>Day</hi> be Executed upon Them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> that now are, are Reſerv'd for <hi>Fire</hi> at that <hi>Day,</hi> and that Chriſt, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 7, 8. ſhall be <hi>Reveal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d in Flames of Fire,</hi> taking <hi>Vengeance;</hi> and that as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſays; The <hi>Day of the Lord Cometh as a Theif in the Night,</hi> in which, the <hi>Heavens ſhall paſs away with a Great Noiſe,</hi> and the <hi>Elements melt</hi> with <hi>Fervent Heat,</hi> and the <hi>Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Works that are therein, ſhall be Burnt up,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 10. and again, <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>Looking for,</hi> and <hi>Haſting unto the Day of God,</hi> wherein the <hi>Heavens being on Fire, ſhall be diſſolv'd,</hi> and the <hi>Elements ſhall melt with Fervent Heat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing the very <hi>Revelation</hi> of Chriſt, is in <hi>Flames of Fire,</hi> as <hi>Lightning;</hi> and that our Lord compares his <hi>Coming</hi> to the <hi>Flood on the Old World,</hi> and the <hi>Fire,</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone on Sodom,</hi> the <hi>very ſame day that</hi> Noah <hi>enter'd into the Ark,</hi> and <hi>Lot went out of Sodom. Luke</hi> 17. 27, 28. The Conflagration muſt be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration before the Judgment, or Inſtantaneous with the Beginning of that <hi>Day,</hi> and ſo I ſuppoſe is the Judgment of all Divines.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Wicked Alive ſhall be ſpeedily by this <hi>Fire,</hi> brought into the ſame Condition with the Dead Wicked, Raiſed to ſhare in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Perdition:</hi> For the <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earth that now are,</hi> are <hi>Kept in Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97298:4"/> 
               <hi>for the Day of Judgment,</hi> and the <hi>Perdition of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly Men.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Seeing the Apoſtle Expreſly teaches, <hi>v.</hi> 13. That we <hi>Look for New Heavens</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> wherein <hi>Righteouſneſs ſhall dwell;</hi> It is moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture, that the <hi>New Heavens</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> ſhould come as a <hi>Veſſel out of the Refiner's Fire,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs dwell therein.</hi> So that the <hi>New Heaven</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> immediately <hi>Come out of this Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this I look upon as ſo Agreeable to Scripture, and the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Senſe of it, that whoever keeps Inviolate this <hi>Form of Sound Words,</hi> cannot fall into any Great Error, I then making a Solemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that I am Fully perſwaded of all theſe Things, even to a <hi>Plero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phory</hi> of <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> and ſuppoſing All Sober Chriſtians herein to Joyn with me, I paſs forward with Greater Aſſurance.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The particular Preciſe State of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> as in this Judiciary State, ſhall be <hi>deliver'd</hi> up at ſome Time to <hi>God and to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and ſo the Kingdom and State of <hi>Eternity</hi> ſucceed, I do alſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is the Univerſal Faith of Sober Chriſtians; Although the <hi>New Heavens</hi> and <hi>New Earth</hi> may be ſuppos'd to continue for ever, as They are by Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> and, as I Remember, by that ſo excellent Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Calvin</hi> on the aforenam'd Text, and very probably by many other Great <hi>Theologers,</hi> and <hi>Scripture-Interpreters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from all theſe Principles lay'd together, ſeveral Points are Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed upon the Conſideration of the General Doctrine of the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> that are ready to be charg'd as Unreaſonableneſſes, or Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripturiſms on the Doctrine of tho Thouſand Years Kingdom; which compar'd with what is taught univerſally of Chriſt coming to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will be as a Load taken off from it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Seeing the <hi>Day of Judgment</hi> is a middle State of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> between the preſent State, and the State of Eternity; It is hence undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, There is a middle <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or middle State of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When a Diſpenſation, or Oeconomy for the Divine Glory, as for <hi>Judgment</hi> Requires it, It is no diſhonour to Chriſt to come from the <hi>Right Hand of God,</hi> where He is <hi>Exalted</hi> above All <hi>Heavens</hi> into the Lower State of the World, much leſs Degradation from preſent Glory for <hi>Saints</hi> to <hi>Come with Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Nor does Chriſt ſuffer any diminution of Glory, when He Goes back to <hi>Heaven,</hi> the Buſineſs of ſuch <hi>Oeconomy,</hi> as of <hi>Judgment,</hi> being diſpatch'd.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is ſufficient Security in the midſt of the Conflagration for the Bodies of Saints, whether Riſen or Chang'd, though we cannot define how.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Nor ſhall the Bodies of the wicked, however puniſh'd, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd in theſe Flames.</p>
            <p n="6">6. There is no Abſurdity on Scripture Account to ſuppoſe a manifold Change of Body according to the Variation of States.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97298:5"/>
            <p n="7"> 7. There will be Found Room for the Bodies of all, both <hi>Riſen</hi> and <hi>Changed</hi> Saints; as alſo of all the wicked according to the General Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Day of Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. A <hi>New Heaven</hi> and a <hi>New Earth,</hi> and by Conſequence a Reſtitution of All Things, are in the very Letter to be Expected according to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
            <p>Now whatever may according to Scripture, and without any Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to the Great Principles Notions, and Senſe of it, be ſuppos'd for a Leſſer, or ſo much, as Any Time, may be ſuppos'd for a longer Time, even for ſo long, as Scripture gives us any Reaſon to extend it unto, ſeeing There is no Scripture Inconſiſtency in the Fundamental Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
            <p>And now there being ſuch a Foundation lay'd in that, which is Agreed among all Chriſtians, if there ſhall be Any Inducement from Scripture to do it, we may Build upon this Foundation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſeeing Chriſt ſhall Appear from Heaven, with his Saints in a <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Triumph, and Glory over his Enemies, and that there is no Signification of the Time of duration, Contradictory to that of a 1000 Years; and at leaſt one Great Signification, It is a 1000 Years, Why may we not Conclude, the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is a <hi>Kingdom</hi> of a 1000 Years?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Seeing there ſhall be a <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth,</hi> that ſhall <hi>come forth as a Veſſel for the Finer</hi> out of the Conflagration, and that there is Great Reaſon to think; That They ſhall be both inhabited: Why may not the <hi>Saints of the Reſurrection, Equal to the Angels,</hi> Inhabit the <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> and the <hi>Saints Chan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d,</hi> who are ſo peculiarly called twice the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; The <hi>Living<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the <hi>Remaining,</hi> (as a moſt peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Generation of Saints that Chriſt ſo Holds in his Hand, as, that They can no more Fall, as may be Surmized, then the Saints Above, who are as <hi>Angels</hi> confirm'd;) Inhabit the <hi>New Earth,</hi> as <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould have done, a 1000 Years? Eſpecially, ſeeing It is ſuppoſeable It ſhall be Inhabited, and we Know not Any, who ſhall Inhabit it, God knoweth only who ſhall Inhabit it, Except theſe <hi>Living Remaining Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Seeing it is Agreed, The Adminiſtration of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as at the <hi>Day of Judgment</hi> ſhall not Laſt to Eternity; and that Chriſt, and All his Saints Aſcend up to God, and that <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Judgment</hi> Ends; Why may not this be the Senſe of thoſe ſo Weighty Words of the Apoſtle, concerning the <hi>Son's delivering up the Kingdom,</hi> of his being <hi>Subject,</hi> and of God, being <hi>All in All?</hi> or what elſe is ſo likely as this of the <hi>Son</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning up that Illuſtrious Appearing viſible Glory, that He ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with, during that <hi>Judicatory Kingdom,</hi> ſeeing it is a <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Triumph and Victory, that is ſo <hi>Deliver'd up?</hi> And why ſhould it not be the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of a 1000 Years? Seeing the naming a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> though of a 1000 Years, yet becauſe It is but of a 1000 Years, Implys It ſhall end; And as the Apoſtle makes plain, in that it is a Reign, till <hi>All his Enemies are put under his Feet;</hi> It is a <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Victory and Triumph, Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97298:5"/> and Ending in <hi>putting down Enemies,</hi> as <hi>Judgment</hi> muſt needs do, and then <hi>Given up to God.</hi> And thus there is an eaſie Slide from the Acknowledged, and moſt General Doctrine of the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> into what the Scripture ſays of a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or <hi>Reign of Christ</hi> for a 1000 Years; For it is expreſly ſaid, There were <hi>Thrones,</hi> as of a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> was Given to Them that ſat upon the <hi>Thrones,</hi> the very word proper to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Day;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey that <hi>Sate</hi> upon the <hi>Thrones,</hi> muſt needs be Chriſt and his Saints; For They <hi>Lived</hi> and <hi>Reigned</hi> with Chriſt a 1000 Years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 4. And then, It is anew ſaid; <hi>Bleſſed, and Holy is He that hath part,</hi> though not the <hi>Principal, viz.</hi> either as <hi>Saints Riſing,</hi> though not <hi>Martyrs,</hi> or as <hi>Living Remaining Saints;</hi> on ſuch the <hi>Second Death hath no Power.</hi> And then, as at the End of the <hi>Judgment</hi> according to the General Doctrine, Chriſt Reſigns up that <hi>Judiciary Kingdom,</hi> and Returns to God. And as the Apoſtle ſays, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Subdued All Enemies,</hi> He <hi>Gives up the Kingdom;</hi> even ſo the 1000 Years <hi>Kingdom</hi> muſt be Given up, becauſe it is a <hi>Kingdom</hi> only of a 1000 Years.</p>
            <p>And thus the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> Begins with a <hi>Judgment, viz.</hi> of determining, who are Thoſe his Saints, who ſhall Appear in the <hi>Glory</hi> and Bleſſedneſs of it, even of that <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> as Saints <hi>Rais'd,</hi> or as Saints <hi>Living and Remaining,</hi> but <hi>Chang'd;</hi> and who, as <hi>Enemies,</hi> ſhall lye at the <hi>Footſtool of Chriſt's Feet, Slain with the Sword of his Mouth,</hi> and as the <hi>Dead,</hi> and yet in Viſible Bodies under <hi>Contempt</hi> and <hi>Diſhonour,</hi> and as the Trophies of the victorious Wrath of Chriſt; And this <hi>Kingdom</hi> Ends with a <hi>Judgment,</hi> even the Giving up all this Saints in perfect Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and Incorruptibility to his <hi>Father</hi> to Enjoy him for ever, and with that perfect <hi>Subduing</hi> All the Wicked Angels and Men, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Catargeſis,</hi> or <hi>deſtroying,</hi> and the <hi>Apocalyptic</hi> Apoſtle a <hi>Caſting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lake;</hi> And becauſe This is Final, and Conſummate; therefore. He Repreſents the whole Judiciary Proceeding, and ſets out the <hi>Dead,</hi> as Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd from all the Receptacles of <hi>Death</hi> from whence They Came, and were Judg'd at the Beginning of the 1000 Years, which <hi>Judgment</hi> is Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd and Ratified, and Fill'd up at the End of the 1000 Years, and the Execution alſo; There being this only Difference between the Beginning and End of the 1000 Years in Relation to Them, that They are at the Beginning, and during the whole Space of the 1000 Years, made the <hi>Footſtool of the Feet of Chriſt,</hi> and afterwards under the Final deſtruction of being <hi>Caſt into the Lake.</hi> This therefore takes away the Objection of the <hi>New Earth,</hi> having ſuch an abundance of Wicked in it; For They Lye as Captives, and Slaves of Juſtice, that can neither Annoy, nor defile that State; So that there is a Glory of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in, and with his Saints above and below, during the whole Time of the 1000 Years, and a Government every way Agreeable, and no difference between the General Doctrine of Chriſtians concerning the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> and what I Affirm, except the duration of the 1000 Years; For who can but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97298:6"/> ſay? That <hi>Day</hi> ſhall be a <hi>Day of Glory</hi> to Chriſt and his Saints, both <hi>Rais'd</hi> and <hi>Chang'd,</hi> as in viſible Bodies of Glory; of Horror, Diſhonour, and Puniſhment to the Wicked in viſible Bodies of Contempt and Shame? That they can neither Trouble, nor Pollute that Day, nor State, any more then They do the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity,</hi> though They are never ſo many in their own place, or Hell; That theſe viſible Heavens and Earth ſhall be ſo chang'd by the Glorious Coming of the <hi>Judge,</hi> and his Saints, That They ſhall be <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth;</hi> That there muſt be Room for all Good and Bad, in whatever ſhall be ſuppos'd to be the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torium,</hi> the Hall of Juſtice at that Time; That Chriſt and his Saints come from the higheſt Heaven for that purpoſe; That Wicked Men come from Earth and Hell. And that Chriſt and his Saints Return, this Glorious Adminiſtration being at an End, to that Higheſt Heaven, to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Father,</hi> with this <hi>Judiciary Kingdom</hi> Given up to Him, and <hi>Sathan</hi> and All the Wicked <hi>Caſt</hi> to the <hi>Lake;</hi> So that I ſay again, here is no difference, but only of the 1000 Years Continuance; And to the Proof of that, I now proceed.</p>
            <p>And I will do it in greateſt Brevity in this Method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I will propoſe the Scripture-Model of this State, which it ſelf will ſhew the Rationality of it ſelf, and as in a State of duration.</item>
               <item>2. I will ſuper-add to the Arguments I have given, new Ones, That there is ſuch a State to be, and of a 1000 Years duration, and no more; and Anſwer the moſt Formidable Objections more Fully.</item>
               <item>3. I will Argue againſt any <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> or Scripture Model, that can be given in Bar, of what I now give.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I Begin with the Firſt, the Rationality of the Scripture-Model.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There ſhall be an Exaltation of the Humane Nature of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, in viſible Glory, in oppoſition to that unrevealed State, wherein the <hi>Heavens Now contain Him,</hi> and alſo in oppoſition to, and Recompenſe of the Depreſſions, and Humiliation, it was under in his firſt Coming, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that every <hi>Knee may bow to Him,</hi> and every <hi>Tongue confeſs that He is Lord,</hi> to the <hi>Glory of God the Father; Every Eye ſhall ſee Him, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mouth of his Servants ſhall praiſe Him, and none of his Enemies be able to gain ſay:</hi> The Loweſt Creation, <hi>Things in Earth,</hi> and <hi>under the Earth,</hi> ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, as They can, Bleſs Him; This <hi>Appearing</hi> is the <hi>Sign of the Son of Man,</hi> that ſhall be ſeen in the <hi>Clouds.</hi> That All this ſhall be at the <hi>Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> no Chriſtian will deny; I lengthen it out the 1000 Years.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There muſt be an Appearance of the Glory of the <hi>Redemption of Chriſt</hi> in its full Luſtre; To <hi>this</hi> End, the Saints of the firſt <hi>Reſurrection</hi> muſt be ſeen in Robes, waſh'd white in his Blood, as Kings and Prieſts to God and the Father, and Reigning <hi>over,</hi> rather then <hi>upon</hi> the <hi>Earth,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>over,</hi> not <hi>upon many Things will I make thee Ruler, Revel.</hi> 5. 10. with <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 21. <hi>They have Palms of Victory in</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97298:6"/> 
               <hi>their Hands;</hi> The <hi>Bride</hi> the <hi>Lambs Wife</hi> is Adorn'd, and it is Granted to Her to be <hi>Arrayed in Linnen, White and Clean,</hi> which is the <hi>Righteouſneſs of the Saints.</hi> The <hi>Armies of Heaven</hi> that is, Theſe <hi>Saints</hi> follow, <hi>Cloth'd</hi> alſo in <hi>Fine Linnen, White and Clean;</hi> They <hi>have the Name of the Lamb in their Foreheads,</hi> even as of God, <hi>Revel. c.</hi> 19. <hi>c</hi> 20. The <hi>Saints Living;</hi> and <hi>Remaining,</hi> who partake of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrestion,</hi> are Prieſts alſo, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of God, but of Chriſt, and <hi>Reign</hi> with Him a 1000 Years. And from this Glory of <hi>Redemption,</hi> It is impoſſible for the Saints, either of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> or the <hi>Living Remaining, partaking of the Firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> to fall, as it is for the Redeemer himſelf to fail; as I always aſſert, particularly in my laſt Anſwer; For the <hi>Second Death</hi> elſe might, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can, never ſhall have <hi>Power over Them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the Appearance of this Glory of <hi>Redemption,</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection</hi> ſhall have Bodies of that Spirituality, Incorruptible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Immortality, as to be equal to the <hi>Angels,</hi> ſo that in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Thing, as it ſhall then be Founded by God, They cannot dye any more, being the <hi>Children of God,</hi> and of the <hi>Reſurrection:</hi> And this is given firſt to the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> as a peculiar Recompenſe for the many Terrors, and Debaſements, Death Brings with it. The <hi>Saints</hi> therefore <hi>Living,</hi> and <hi>Remaining,</hi> who <hi>Dye</hi> not, nor ſhall ſuffer the Diſhonour, Pain, the Terror of dying, are upon the Ballance of Things, for the Glory of God, and Chriſt, in this <hi>Oeconomy,</hi> not till the 1000 Years are ended, and They <hi>Caught up,</hi> inveſted with this Glory; and are therefore ſaid, till then, only to be <hi>Partakers</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> They have therefore Bodies <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g'd</hi> into the moſt excellent <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſiac</hi> State, as <hi>Adam</hi> had before ſin, and probably, as much excelling, as the <hi>Firſt Adam</hi> is excell'd by the <hi>Second.</hi> And though they for many great Reſons, Beget an Off-ſpring to the Mediator, and <hi>Eat,</hi> and <hi>Drink,</hi> as <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould have done, and All this in the Holieſt, Pureſt manner, ſuch excellent Bodies can be Exalted into; and though They do not Immediately put on <hi>Incoeruption</hi> and <hi>Iwmortality,</hi> till they are <hi>Caught up;</hi> Yet They in event, can no more dye, nor fall away, then the Saints above, All which Anſwers many Objections concerning them. And It Redounds Infinitely to the Glory of the Redeemer, and of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am</hi> above the <hi>Firſt,</hi> that in a poſſibility of dying, as to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Things; They who might, as <hi>Adam,</hi> dye, and Fall; Yet ſecur'd by the Media<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or, They ſhall not dye, nor Fall, but They ſhall be <hi>Caught</hi> up, and put on <hi>Incorruption</hi> and <hi>Immo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tality:</hi> And when <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Sin</hi> are thus every way ſubdued in the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated out of their Hands, and in the <hi>Saints chang'd,</hi> preſerv'd from their <hi>Sting,</hi> even under a poſſibility; Then are They both <hi>Swallowed up in Victory</hi> by Chriſt, Appearing thus every way a perfect Redeemer, on which Account, as one Reaſon, All is thus ordered; Then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> with all its <hi>Dead;</hi> and <hi>Sathan,</hi> the Prince of All, <hi>Thrown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lake,</hi> and the Triumphal Song ſung; the Effect of which, endures throughout All Eternity.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97298:7"/>
            <p n="3"> 3. The Saints of Chriſt, principally the Martyrs and Sufferers, and the Contemn'd, Abuſed, Perſecuted, and Beheaded for the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and the <hi>Teſtimony which They Held,</hi> with All who have Reſiſted the Impurity and Corruptions of the World, ſhall Appear in Glory, ſown in Weakneſs, but Rais'd in Power, Sown in Diſhonour, Rais'd in Glory, Bearing the Image of the <hi>Heavenly Adam,</hi> the <hi>Quickning Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> not only in <hi>Heaven,</hi> but from <hi>Heaven,</hi> as in a <hi>Kingdom</hi> low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then the higheſt <hi>Heaven, Sitting on Thrones,</hi> and <hi>Judgment is Given to Them</hi> for the 1000 Years:</p>
            <p n="4">4. For this Glory of Chriſt the Redeemer, and of his Redemption, and of his Saints; There is a Glory of the Renewed Reſtored Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the viſible <hi>Heavens,</hi> and all their Influences Purified and Purg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d, and ſo made new; and the <hi>Earth</hi> Renewed in the ſame manner, that the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection</hi> may Appear as a <hi>Firmament,</hi> and ſhine as the <hi>Stars, Dan.</hi> 12. even as the <hi>Sun, Matth.</hi> 13. 43. upon the <hi>New Earth,</hi> and have a proſpect of Beauty, and Purity. And the <hi>Saints on Earth,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Call'd <hi>Nations of the Saved.</hi>
               </note> All, as <hi>Kings of the Earth, Revel.</hi> 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24, 25. may <hi>Walk in this Light of the New Jeruſalem</hi> above, and <hi>Bring their Glory to it,</hi> in looking upon their Communion with it, as their Higheſt Glory; and ſo the whole <hi>Creation</hi> may be deliver'd from the <hi>Bondage of Corruption,</hi> into the Glorious Liberty of the <hi>Sons of God,</hi> for which it now Groans in its preſent Slavery, and with earneſtneſs <hi>Waits;</hi> Even as in all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, There is an Appetite Implanted by <hi>Creation</hi> to See, and Enjoy a due Time in the Glory of Gods <hi>Creation,</hi> fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the Curſe, and Adorn'd with the Bleſſings of it; This we ſee how ſtrongly it now works in the Holieſt Men and Women; however in Regard, This is not the Place, nor State, nor Time, it be mix<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d with much Corruption, and as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>Lust</hi> in a World, to which God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Heart can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be; and therefore He often chaſtiſes with Great Severity the over eager deſires in any of his <hi>Sts.</hi> of Any Thing here; But then there ſhall be ſuch a State, that the <hi>Lord Himſelf</hi> ſhall <hi>Rejoyce in his Works</hi> with all his Saints <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing</hi> in the <hi>Works of his Hands,</hi> when there ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be an <hi>Apocataſtaſis,</hi> a Reſtitution of All Things, without which, the <hi>Second Adam</hi> would not be as perfect a Reſtorer, as the <hi>Firſt Adam</hi> was a Deſolator; But I Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, and ſhall after prove the <hi>Flying away</hi> of this <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> and that therefore this <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>conomy</hi> laſts but a 1000 Years, as the <hi>Sabbatiſm</hi> of the Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y of Creation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There muſt be a State, Bearing ſome Proport<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on to all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed; of a <hi>City,</hi> and a <hi>Country,</hi> and of <hi>Nations,</hi> and a <hi>Poſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rity,</hi> as the <hi>Stars of Heaven,</hi> as the <hi>Duſt of the Earth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 13. 16.</note> and as the <hi>Sand on the Sea ſhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Innumerable,</hi> that He may be a <hi>Father of many Nations,</hi> and <hi>Heir of the World;</hi> of all which, <hi>Canaan</hi> and <hi>Jerulalem,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17.</note> and the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were but <hi>Types;</hi> For this was a <hi>Heavenly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> as the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a Poſterity of True, and Sincere Believers; How can this then be better explain'd, then by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97298:7"/> 
               <hi>the New Jeruſalem coming down from Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> a Poſterity, as the <hi>Stars,</hi> for whom he Knows how to make Room, who hath done it for thoſe vaſt Globes of Light; and then by the <hi>New Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Saints Living,</hi> and <hi>Remaining</hi> on the <hi>New Earth,</hi> who ſhall be as the <hi>Dust,</hi> and as the <hi>Sand:</hi> And He will make Room for Them, who hath <hi>ſtretched out this Earth for them that walk upon it;</hi> and wherein beſides the much leſs Cumber of <hi>Paradiſiac Bodies,</hi> and the Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Sufficiency of the <hi>Paradiſiac Earth,</hi> and Purity of the Air, and the <hi>Leaves of the Tree of Life,</hi> for the <hi>Healing the Nations;</hi> There is Proviſion for all Enjoyments of the <hi>Saints</hi> in thoſe Bodies; Beſides all this, There ſhall be no <hi>Sea</hi> to to take up Room, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. 1. as there was not in the <hi>Firſt Paradiſiac Earth,</hi> as hath been made out by that Truly Excellent The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oriſt, Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> Maſter of the <hi>Charter-Houſe;</hi> Giving Great Light to that <hi>Apocalyptical</hi> Text, and Receiving Great Proof from it.</p>
            <p>And herein for his ſake, who <hi>God over All, Bleſſed for ever,</hi> came of Them; and for the <hi>Believed Father's ſakes,</hi> and according to all the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and Language of <hi>Poophecy:</hi> The Spiritual Natural <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall have a Preeminence, and for which They ſhall certainly be call'd, though it will Remain a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> until the ſet Time of the <hi>Gentiles Fullneſs</hi> be come; But in the mean Time for their ſakes, the <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Heaven</hi> and <hi>New Earth</hi> is call'd <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſo many <hi>Apocalyptical</hi> Figures are derived from Them, leading to that <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. There ſhall be a plain, ſenſible, and viſible State of the Wicked in <hi>Diſhonour,</hi> and <hi>Contempt,</hi> in the View of All; For all the Falſe Glory, Riches, and Pleaſure, They have here Abuſed, They ſhall Receive double, and that in Bodies of Diſgrace; The General Doctrine of the <hi>Day of Judgment</hi> concerning the Wicked cannot but Acknowledge this to be according to Scripture; For It is moſt certain, ſuch ſhall be their Appearance, ſignifyed by their being <hi>Goats on the Left Hand, Matt.</hi> 25. 33. in the Grand Aſſembly of the <hi>Great Day;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven in Bodies of viſible Shame and Horror; None will deny this in, and for that Day, and for ſo long, how long ſoever that Day laſts; For what is no Incompoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility for any Time of that <hi>Day,</hi> is poſſible for all that <hi>Day</hi> or Time; And at the End of that <hi>Day</hi> or Time, They are <hi>Caſt into the Lake,</hi> where, as to the <hi>Pain of Senſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as well as to the <hi>Pain of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſs,</hi> I Agree with all <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> or Sacred Doctrine; All that I Add, is in the Words of <hi>Prophecy;</hi> Theſe Viſibly <hi>Dead</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw, or Condemn'd by their very Appearance, <hi>Lived</hi> not until the 1000 Years were Finiſh'd, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is, not at all in the Great Senſes of Life; For it is Immediately ſaid, The <hi>Second Death ſhall have no Power over the Partakers</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> Imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, All the <hi>Dead,</hi> not <hi>Partakers</hi> Fall under the <hi>Second Death;</hi> But ſeeing They were not yet <hi>Caſt into the Lake,</hi> though for the 1000 Y. They lye unactive: They at the end of Them had that Kind of Revival to Joyn in that ſhort Attempt ef <hi>Compaſſing the Beloved City,</hi> whether by way of Temptation to Defection, as on <hi>Adam</hi> in his <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> or of ſuch violence,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97298:8"/> as <hi>Sathan</hi> us'd upon <hi>Job,</hi> or both, (but neither with poſſibility of Succeſs, to the Glory of the Redeemer) They Joyn'd as Devils of an Inferiour order with <hi>Sathan Prince of Devils,</hi> under his Superior Influence of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, call'd Alluſively <hi>Deception:</hi> But in the very Attempt, <hi>Sathan</hi> firſt, and his <hi>Angels</hi> of the Higher Diabolic order, and then the <hi>Dead</hi> are <hi>Caſt</hi> with <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> into the <hi>Lake,</hi> to the <hi>Devil</hi> and his <hi>Angels, Matt.</hi> 25. 41. whereby thereis an utter Suppreſſion of all poſſible Action a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Divine Kingdom</hi> for ever; but no Ceſſation of that Action or Receptiveneſs neceſſary to the <hi>Suffering</hi> All, that is to be underſtood by the <hi>Vengeance of Eternal Fire,</hi> as Scripture declares, which I never ſo much as call'd into Queſtion, much leſs once denied.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe it is ſo ordered by God, that here would be the laſt At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, it is call'd a <hi>Gathering to Battel,</hi> as it were to try their utmoſt at this laſt deciſive Point, according to no unuſual <hi>Symbol</hi> in this <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. This State ſhall be to the Saints above and below, a Preparation to an <hi>Eternal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion to God and to the Father, by Jeſus Christ,</hi> in ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable State of Oneneſs, as leaves no poſſible Thought of ſuch Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away, as of the <hi>Angels</hi> from their <hi>Firſt Eſtate;</hi> or of <hi>Adam from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe;</hi> as I always have and do Declare; And this is the <hi>Glorioas Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation</hi> of <hi>the Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and not a diſhonourable <hi>Spewing out of Christ's Mouth,</hi> as ſhall be preſently more fully Declared<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration is conveyed to us in ſuch Expreſſions, as are moſt Evidently made Eſſential to the State of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſo (as ſhall be ſeen) to the <hi>Thouſand Years.</hi> They are alſo moſt proper to ſuch a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, <hi>viz. The Lord God and the Lamb</hi> are the <hi>Temple of that City,</hi> They <hi>gives it Light.</hi> The <hi>Throne of God and of the Lamb</hi> art in it; They <hi>See His Face; His Servants ſerve him; his Name is in their Foreheads; They eat of the Tree of Life, and drink of the Fountain of the Water of Life,</hi> as the Higheſt Initiation, Pledge and Aſſurance of the Simp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, Abſolute <hi>Eternal Life, to which Fountain the Lamb leads them.</hi> Rev. 20. 6. <hi>c.</hi> 21. 6. 22. 24. <hi>c.</hi> 22. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>c.</hi> 7. 17.</p>
            <p>Now if it ſhall be proved, the <hi>New Heaven</hi> and the <hi>New Earth</hi> of this State ſhall <hi>Fly away,</hi> and yet that the State it ſelf cannot End, but Iſſues into that Abſolute <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> wherein <hi>God is All in All;</hi> then it will be made plain, this State however High above Expreſſion, compar'd with that now, yet if compar'd to that Eternal State of <hi>God All in All,</hi> it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut Initiation and Preparation, though of the Higheſt Degree, of Spirits in Bodies for an Union to God in this Eternal State.</p>
            <p>And our Lord Concurs in his <hi>Mediatory Prayer,</hi> John 17. 21. 23. That there ſhall be a State of his <hi>Saints</hi> ſo Viſibly Glorious, as to ſtrike the Wicked, call'd the <hi>World,</hi> with <hi>Conviction;</hi> That ſuch a State (as it is Initially ſo, while They behold it) cannot but Iſſue in Everlaſting U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God by Chriſt, and in the <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Glory, Jeſus Christ,</hi> as the <hi>Eternal Word Miſſion'd by the Father</hi> into our Nature, had with the <hi>Father</hi> before the <hi>World Began;</hi> And therefore in regard of <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97298:8"/> 
               <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> with the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> he is ſaid to have it even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Exiſtence of the <hi>Humane Nature;</hi> of which Miſſion there ſhall alſo be Fulleſt Cenviction.</p>
            <p>And what State can be ſo proper for this, as the <hi>Glorious Kingdom of Christ?</hi> wherein the <hi>Wicked</hi> thus behold with <hi>Horrour</hi> and <hi>Torment,</hi> what ſhall be for ever, while they <hi>caſt into the Lake</hi> ſhall be for ever ſhut out of it.</p>
            <p>I come now to the Second Thing propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſuperadd ſome Arguments to thoſe already given in my Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 1. The Stream of <hi>Prophecy</hi> in all its Expreſſions runs ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently towards ſuch a State; that, however hard ſhifts are made to Evaporate them into <hi>Allegory,</hi> yet <hi>Prophecy</hi> it ſelf will not be ſatisfied without ſuch a <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>New Earth;</hi> wherein ſhall be Univerſal <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Knowledge of God</hi> in Viſible Glory, in Univerſal Peace, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of All Things, Freedom from Evil, no more <hi>Curſe</hi> in Life, and no Death, and all in a State of Duration. Nor will <hi>Atheists</hi> and <hi>Anti-Scripturiſts,</hi> cxacting the <hi>Fulfilling</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> be Convicted, till thoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions are ſo Fulfilled before their Eyes, as indeed they ſhall be; For it becomes not the <hi>Oracles of Supream Truth</hi> to (as I may ſay) Excuſe the unfulfilledneſs of Themſelves in their Higheſt Expreſſions, by the uſe of <hi>Allegory,</hi> or <hi>Metaphor,</hi> or <hi>Rhetorick;</hi> All ſhall therefore have a Juſt Complement; And ſeeing many Refer to ſome <hi>Earth,</hi> and to ſome <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Time;</hi> In ſome <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi> and in ſomè <hi>Earth,</hi> They muſt therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e be Fulfilled, and that is in that State of the <hi>Thuuſand Yoars Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I Argue from the <hi>Prayer</hi> of Chriſt, ſtyl'd the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> which I eſteem particularly prepar'd for the State of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as in a <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth;</hi> Although all Things of the preſent State are alſo, I own, Admirably Comprehended and Fitted to preſent Uſe of <hi>Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Third Petiteon</hi> of that <hi>Prayer</hi> Teacheth us to pray, <hi>Thy Will be done,</hi> not only <hi>upon Earth,</hi> as <hi>in Heaven;</hi> but [As in <hi>Heaven</hi> and on <hi>Earth]</hi> as it is Emphatical in the Original; where alſo it varies the Number from <hi>Heavens;</hi> In the Preface <hi>Heavens;</hi> viz. <hi>Our Father which art in the Heavens,</hi> Plurally; to <hi>[As in Heaven]</hi> in the Single Number, <hi>and on Earth,</hi> with a Singular Favour to a Parallel <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and <hi>New Earth:</hi> And it leads us to pray for the <hi>Doing the Will of God</hi> in ſuch a <hi>Parallel Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Earth;</hi> that as in Paralelliſm, the <hi>Will of God may be done,</hi> as in the One, ſo in the Other.</p>
            <p>Beſides, according to Common Interpretation of this <hi>Petition, A Prayer according to the will of Ood,</hi> ſo exactly as our Lord weighed it out, and that hath been ſo long <hi>prayed</hi> by all his Servants in <hi>Faith</hi> cannot but be <hi>Heard; The Spirit helping their Infirmities, (when they know not what</hi> in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> to <hi>pray for</hi> as <hi>they ought)</hi> with <hi>unutterable Groans,</hi> and <hi>God knows the Mind of his Spirit,</hi> though they do not ſo clearly underſtand this <hi>Prayer;</hi> So then, It muſt be Heard: But it cannot be Heard, if there be not ſuch a State
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97298:9"/> on Earth, in which the <hi>Will of God may be done,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven.</hi> For the <hi>Earth</hi> and the <hi>Earth</hi> as in parallel to <hi>Heaven,</hi> ſo particularly named, is the <hi>Place</hi> or <hi>Baſis,</hi> on which the Saints that do it, ſhall Reſt; So that the <hi>doing the Will of God</hi> in any other State or Place, will not be a <hi>Fulfilling</hi> this <hi>Petition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will the doing it in Sincerity, according to the Meaſure of the Saints now on Earth, anſwer the <hi>Petition.</hi> For our Lord in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> which is in ſuch Number, Weight and Meaſure, would not have layd a Paralled, wherein there is no Equality nor Proportion, as Things are now, <hi>viz.</hi> Between <hi>doing the Will of God on Earth</hi> and in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> For every part of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> ſhall, ere he hath perfected his <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> upon it, be Fulfilled in the Higheſt Senſe of each part; This we know is not yet in any, particularly in this <hi>Petition;</hi> therefore a State ſhall be on purpoſe for it.</p>
            <p>This alſo muſt needs Lock in with the foregoing <hi>Petitions;</hi> when ever there is a <hi>Doing the Will of God ſo on Earth,</hi> his <hi>Name</hi> muſt be <hi>Sanctified as in Heaven</hi> and <hi>upon Earth,</hi> elſe his <hi>Will</hi> cannot be ſo <hi>Done;</hi> becauſe <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying his Name</hi> is ſo Eminently his <hi>Will,</hi> that his <hi>Will</hi> cannot be <hi>Done</hi> as in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>on Earth,</hi> except his <hi>Name</hi> be <hi>Sanstiſſed</hi> as in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>on Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus is it alſo with his <hi>Kingdom coming;</hi> That muſt needs <hi>Come</hi> as in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>upon Earth,</hi> when-ever his <hi>Will</hi> is ſo <hi>Done;</hi> And it cannot <hi>Come</hi> till it is ſo <hi>Done,</hi> and his <hi>Name</hi> ſo <hi>Sanctified;</hi> For what is his <hi>Kingdom</hi> but the <hi>Supream Honour</hi> of our <hi>Kings Name,</hi> and Obedience to his <hi>Will,</hi> ſo Univerſally as in <hi>Heaven?</hi> And whither ſhould this <hi>Kingdom Come</hi> but out of <hi>Heaven,</hi> where-now it is, into a Lower <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth?</hi> where indeed it is in regard of Supream Power always; But it muſt <hi>Come</hi> in a Senſe, it hath not yet <hi>Come.</hi> And if theſe <hi>Three Petitions</hi> were Heard, <hi>As in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth;</hi> The Earth muſt either be a <hi>New Earth</hi> in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for ſuch a Fulfilling, or the Fulfilling would immediately Turn it into a <hi>New Earth:</hi> For ſuch a Change on the Spirits and Actions of Men, and ſuch a Bleſſing from Heaven, as would immediately follow, would make it indeed a <hi>New Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore our Eſteem of this <hi>Prayer</hi> were not too much ſpent in an Ignorant Formality and Superſtition on Bare Words, it would ſoon give us an Unanſwerable Argument of ſuch a <hi>Kingdom on Earth;</hi> and a Kingdom muſt ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a Duration, and what Duration but a <hi>Kingdtm</hi> of that <hi>Thouſand Years, Prophecy</hi> having once named, gives a Preference to? I ſay nothing of the <hi>Petition,</hi> taking in <hi>Heoven, viz</hi> the <hi>Lower Heaven,</hi> which Scripture make the <hi>Habitation of fallen Spirits,</hi> that They being Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, theſe Three Petitions may be Fulfilled there alſo; Nor of the following <hi>Petitions</hi> moſt Adjuſtable hereunto, which I have in a Full Diſcourſe on this <hi>Prayer</hi> made Ready, if God pleaſe to give Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for Publication; as alſo to ſhew the True Laws of our Duty in uſing of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> wherein Men are ſo prone to Run into the very
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97298:9"/> 
               <hi>Battology, Heatheniſm,</hi> or <hi>Vanity</hi> of <hi>Repetition,</hi> as an Antidote againk which, it was given by Chriſt, and this came in by the <hi>Gentiliſm</hi> that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> hath brought into the <hi>Outer Court; Taking</hi> away that <hi>Daily Sacrifice,</hi> the Remains of which are yet among <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 3. With Great Aſſurance, and without any Reluctancy of of Thoughts, I further Argue, That the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> in an eſpecial manner Commiſſion'd for it, by the <hi>Divine Spirit,</hi> hath given the <hi>first Light</hi> to the Knowledge of the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> as a <hi>Kingdom</hi> of a <hi>Thouſand Years, Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. 8. The whole Chapter is indeed a Great <hi>Prophecy</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the State of it; and it carries many ſevere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks on the <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtacy;</hi> as thoſe <hi>Scoffers,</hi> who ſetting up that <hi>Kingdom</hi> in Counterfeit, Burleſque, and Abuſe the <hi>True Kingdom,</hi> and have and ſtill Jeer it out of the Faith of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in Spirit foreſeeing this, Recalls the <hi>Sincere Diſciples of Chriſt</hi> to the <hi>Words of the Prophets</hi> firſt, who are ſo Abundant concerning this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but ſpeak very darkly of the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> or not at all, but through that <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and then to the <hi>Commandment,</hi> or (as the <hi>Learned</hi> Obſerve it to ſignifie) the Doctrine of Us the <hi>Apostles,</hi> of the <hi>Lord and Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe Words are undoubtedly a Preface to what follows after in the Chapter, and therefore to the Doctrine of the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> of the <hi>Thoufand Years,</hi> of the <hi>New Heavens</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> and the holy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences from it, with a very Dreadful <hi>Thunder and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ightning</hi> upon the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> intermixt, and all in cloſe Connexion.</p>
            <p>He promiſes upon theſe <hi>Scoffers,</hi> that They ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all be in the very <hi>Last of Time,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That their Luſts of the preſent World, the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieur and Senſualities of it will oblige them to ſay, <hi>Where is the promiſe of his Coming?</hi> There is no <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> but what we have ſet up; Events of many Ages Demonſtrate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there is no other; Theſe are yet neither <hi>Atheiſts</hi> nor <hi>Anti Scripturiſts,</hi> but ſuch <hi>Mockers</hi> as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaks of, Chapter 28. 22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who will not believe a <hi>Conſumption</hi> on the preſent Earth, to riſe in a greater Harveſt. They allow the Great Change of the World by the <hi>Flood;</hi> the Change by <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> Verſe 13. Inetrprets, as one Principal Branch of the <hi>Promiſe</hi> They Laugh at, and the <hi>Gangrene</hi> Eats beyond <hi>profeſſed Anti-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſm,</hi> as if that <hi>Firſt Reſurrection were paſt already</hi> in that 1000 <hi>Y.</hi> Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Church</hi> ſince <hi>Constantine,</hi> and no other to be expected, but the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inal Judgment</hi> and <hi>Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> Anſwers by laying down this Great <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> which ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle, Lies hid from Them,</hi> Reſolving Obſtinately againſt all Light, <hi>All Things ſhall continue as they were;</hi> that is, They will be Ignorant of any other World.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Theſis</hi> or <hi>Poſition</hi> is, As the Firſt World Deſtroyed by the <hi>Flood</hi> of <hi>Water,</hi> that Lay; as the forenamed Excellent <hi>Theory</hi> hath ſet out, within its own Bowels; And yet that Deſtruction was not till 1656 Years after its Creation; ſo long the <hi>Word of God</hi> Secured it, and there was yet a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97298:10"/> World after it; So the <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> that now are, ſhall be <hi>deſtroyed by Fire,</hi> Hid as it were in its Entrails, for about ſuch a ſpace of Time from the Apoſtle's writing; Till that Appointe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Time, the <hi>ſame Word of God</hi> Interpoſes, and Secures it.</p>
            <p>But ſaith the Apoſt. that you may Rightly Judge of the Poſition, I would by no means <hi>hove you Ignorant of this one Thing,</hi> this Principal Thing in this Point, that I am about to Lead you to, Of the <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth;</hi> That as the <hi>Firſt Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Hoſt of Them Finiſh'd,</hi> and <hi>God's Reſting in them,</hi> was on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and <hi>Seventh Day;</hi> So the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> the Great <hi>Sabbatiſm</hi> of <hi>Reſting</hi> and <hi>Rejoycing</hi> in his <hi>Works,</hi> to God, to Chriſt, and his Saints ſhall be a <hi>Day,</hi> but It is with God, in his Determination, and Counſel concerning it a <hi>Day</hi> of a 1000 Years; and to ſo Great <hi>Day,</hi> He hath made each 1000 Years of the Worlds Continuance a <hi>Day,</hi> and They are <hi>Six,</hi> as at the Worlds <hi>Firſt Creation;</hi> For in the Evening of the <hi>Sixth Millenary,</hi> That <hi>Day</hi> ſhall Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. Think not therefore the <hi>Lord is Slack,</hi> for He hath with Great Wiſdom Ballanc'd, and Weigh'd out for the <hi>Firſt Seventh Day Sabbath,</hi> a <hi>Sahbath</hi> of a 1000 Years; For the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> that will be for <hi>Perdition to the Wicked,</hi> ſhall be a <hi>Day</hi> of a 1000 Years <hi>Reſt</hi> to <hi>the People of God;</hi> and to ſo Great a <hi>Day</hi> of a 1000 Years, He hath with infinite Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to Bring All his own Elect into it, weigh'd out alſo for each <hi>Day</hi> Leading to the <hi>Firſt Sabbath</hi> Six <hi>Millenaries,</hi> or 1000 of Years, which he Accounts, as <hi>Days</hi> to <hi>Gathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in all his Elect, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Heb.</hi> 4. Shews the <hi>Long ſuffering</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> to the ſeveral Ages of his People, to be <hi>Salvation to Them,</hi> till that very <hi>Sabbatiſm</hi> comes, that <hi>Remains to the People of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Great Senſe that lies under the very profitable, and Exs<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellent Diſcourſe of the Apoſtle, taken in Common Senſe; But that There is this Great Senſe, I Argue not only from the Symbols of the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> coming out of the <hi>Floo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and from the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> having <hi>Six days,</hi> and then a <hi>Sabbath</hi> of a 1000 Years, Symboliz'd by the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and the <hi>Six Days of Creation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it; to which the whole Scope of the Apoſtle's Diſcourſe makes it plain, that He Refers: But I Eſpecialy Argue from Theſe Two Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Apoſtle's Great Preface, ſhewing a <hi>Myſtical</hi> Doctrine, as ſuch Prefaces do; <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 51. Now that the longeſt, and ſhorteſt Time with God, the <hi>High,</hi> and <hi>Holy one,</hi> that <hi>Inhabits Eternity,</hi> the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Eternal Being, are All Alike, is an undoubted Principle of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Rational Religion; which All are ſuppoſed to Know; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Great Truth needs no ſuch Preface, as not to be Ignorant of that <hi>One Thing,</hi> there being many other ſo Great Principles of that Order of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion, that ought not to <hi>Lye hid</hi> from Any.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe this would not all Anſwer the Apoſtle's Scope, either with Relation unto the <hi>Scoff</hi> of them, that ſay, <hi>Where is the Promiſe</hi> of his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97298:10"/> coming, not Satisfie, and Comfort the Sincere Chriſtian concerning the delay of that <hi>Coming;</hi> For what Comfort is it to the Sincere Chriſtian to whom Each Minute of delay of the <hi>Coming of Chriſt,</hi> eſpecially under ſuffering, is as an Age, that to an Eternal Being, a <hi>Day</hi> is as a 1000 Y. and a 1000 Years as <hi>One Day?</hi> and how would the <hi>Scoffer</hi> Triumph in this? Each <hi>Day</hi> with God is a 1000 Years, how many 1000 of Years may be then to the <hi>Coming</hi> of Chriſt, when every <hi>Day</hi> with God is a 1000 Years? So many <hi>Days</hi> then, ſo many 1000 Years; And if He Counts a 1000 Years but as <hi>One Day,</hi> how long may He delay, e're the coming of Chriſt be? The Comfort proper to this Caſe muſt be ſuch, as is proper to the Creatures of Time: What is proper to the Alone Paramount Eternal Being, Flys too High, and Alought over this Caſe, however an Admirable a Truth it is in it ſelf, and God moſt Adorable in it.</p>
            <p>Nor is there therefore Any Cauſe to vilifie this <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe It is but a 1000 Years, and that a 1000 Years is with God but as a <hi>Day;</hi> Becauſe even according to the Letter of this Scripture, each <hi>Day</hi> of the 1000 Years is with God as a 1000 Years, as well as the 1000 Years, but as <hi>One Day;</hi> when therefore we may by this <hi>Apoſtolic Canon,</hi> if we had Reſpect to the Letter, Count every <hi>Day</hi> of the 1000 Years <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> as a 1000 Years it ſelf; how Great then would it be! But I have ſole Reſpect to the <hi>Myſtic</hi> meaning; That God, the Lord of Time knows, how much, and no more, is proper to his Ends, hath Reſolv'd; A <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batiſm</hi> of a 1000 Years, Beginning with, and Ending with a Grand <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and its middle Space a <hi>Judgment,</hi> or Government according to, and with Relation to thoſe Two Grand <hi>Judgments,</hi> and ſo moſt Fitly call'd <hi>Judgment,</hi> or <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> ſhall be a perfection of Time, and the <hi>Fullneſs of All Times,</hi> and the duration of the <hi>Kingdom of his Son,</hi> as <hi>Son of Man;</hi> And that <hi>Six Days,</hi> each <hi>Day</hi> as a <hi>Milennium,</hi> or 1000 Y. of his <hi>Patience,</hi> and <hi>Long ſuffering</hi> for the <hi>Veſſels of Wrath, Fitting Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Deſtruction</hi> at that <hi>Day;</hi> and for the <hi>Gathering his Elect</hi> from the ſeveral Ages of the World, as well as from the <hi>Four Winds,</hi> ſhall go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it: And it ſelf from its Beginning to its End, ſhall bear this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter; <hi>Fullneſs of Times;</hi> without Nice diſtinction of one part from Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo <hi>Eternity</hi> enſues; and this State, (which ſhews the Fitneſs of the <hi>Symbols)</hi> ſhall have <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth</hi> according to <hi>Creation,</hi> according to the Great <hi>Promiſe, Eſay.</hi> 65. <hi>c</hi> 66. which alſo ſhews the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite State of the <hi>Carcaſes</hi> under a <hi>never dying Worm,</hi> and an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nquencha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Fire,</hi> to mean much higher then the <hi>Carcaſſes of the Aſſirians,</hi> whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Type that ſlaughter might be.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That this <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> hath alſo Great Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> State, I obſerve by Indications, however They may ſeem ſmall, yet are moſt Significant.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97298:11"/>
            <p n="1"> 1. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearnedneſs, Barbarity,</hi> and <hi>Ignorance,</hi> moſt <hi>Natural to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> (however ſince the <hi>Reformation,</hi> Neceſſity hath made his Party more <hi>Learned)</hi> taken notice of in the Word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>verſe</hi> 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> as <hi>Wandring</hi> and <hi>falling Stars,</hi> (as the <hi>Papacy</hi> it lelf is alſo <hi>Symboliz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d</hi> by a <hi>Star falling</hi> from <hi>Heaven</hi> to the <hi>Earth,</hi> Revel. 9. <hi>v.</hi> 1) is Signified by a <hi>Diſ-firmamented State,</hi> in the Word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, wander'd from their <hi>Firmament;</hi> and <hi>Christians</hi> exhorted to <hi>Take heed of falling from their own Firmament,</hi> or <hi>Firmation,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Verſe 17. That <hi>They may ſhine</hi> as that <hi>Firmament,</hi> Dan 12. 3.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Their <hi>Wreſting</hi> of <hi>Scriptures</hi> to their <hi>own Perdition</hi> Univerſally, more Particularly the <hi>Prophecies</hi> for their own <hi>Papal Kingdom,</hi> and againſt the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> And that Diſcourſe of the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. They Writhe wholly from Themſelves, which, would They have Obſerved it, and ask'd, as <hi>Judas</hi> their <hi>Type, Is it I?</hi> It would have Anſwered Them as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did Him, <hi>Thou ſayeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Great <hi>Brand</hi> by which the <hi>Son of Perdition</hi> with all his <hi>Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents may be known,</hi> whoſe <hi>Character</hi> is as the <hi>Judaſſes</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Church, Son of Perdition,</hi> and Two Times <hi>Going into Perdition;</hi> Compare <hi>John</hi> 17. 12. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2 13. <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Theſe Remarks upon the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi>'s <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as I ſtyle it, I have been larger upon, to ſhew I am Conſcious of no Recoyl of Mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, and though ſome Things may ſeem wiredrawn; yet the <hi>Manner</hi> and <hi>Symmetry</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> the Great Rule of its <hi>Interpretation,</hi> will Juſtifie me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 4. I do indeed ſo Rely upon the <hi>Prophecy, Revel.</hi> 20. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> that if I had only that <hi>Scripture,</hi> I ſhould think it ſufficient, although it be but One; and, although it be <hi>Propheick:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I find the Letter ſo Expreſs, as that the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are no leſs than Six ſeveral Times Named; And I Obſerve the <hi>Apostle's</hi> Diſcourſe upon <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> ſo Weighty, ſo Large, with ſo ſevere a Reproof of the Unteachableneſs of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> concerning it, <hi>Heb. c</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. with Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erence to it throughout, <hi>c</hi> 7. All of it; to be Suſpended upon One ſingle <hi>Oracle,</hi> and that <hi>Prophetick</hi> alſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 4. <hi>The Lord hath Sworn, and will not Repent, Thou art a Prieſt for ever after the Order of</hi> Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech, Referring to a ſmall Hiſtorick <hi>Memoir, Geneſ.</hi> 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18. 19, 20. and that on purpoſe Contriv'd to be Dark and under a <hi>Vei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Yet the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſeverely Reproves a <hi>Dulneſs of Hearing of it;</hi> Whereas the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> then might have ſaid, We Deſire only plainer, more undoubted Truths, more genearlly Treated; <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>fundamental Points;</hi> But the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> Silently Threatens the Danger of <hi>Ayoſtacy</hi> on not <hi>Going on to Perfection,</hi> by grounding his ſo Earneſt <hi>Exhortation,</hi> to <hi>Go on,</hi> upon that Danger of <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> without ſo Doing. And indeed there is Great Reaſon to think, a Prediction of the Great <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtacy</hi> (in the Bulk not to be <hi>Repented of,</hi> not to be <hi>Renewed to Repentance,</hi> according to <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vel.</hi> 16.) is lodg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d in it; and that That very <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> came in upon the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97298:11"/> 
               <hi>Ignorance</hi> of, and not <hi>Acquieſcency</hi> in Chriſt's <hi>Melchiſedechian Prieſthood,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Power of an endleſs Life;</hi> but ſetting up that <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Prieſthood</hi> in Counterfeit. For what is the <hi>Melchiſedechian Prieſthood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but a <hi>Prieſthood on a Throne, Zech.</hi> 6. 13? And what is the <hi>Papacy</hi> but a Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit of that, a <hi>Prieſt on a Throne?</hi> (the Falſe <hi>Propbecy</hi> Included alſo, as the True is in the <hi>Prieſthood of Chriſt.)</hi> And why was this <hi>Golden Calf Idolatry</hi> brought in by that <hi>falſe Aaron,</hi> as his <hi>Vicar?</hi> but to ſupply the <hi>Abſence of Chriſt, Gone up to the Mount;</hi> and not knowing, That it is <hi>Witneſſed of him, He liveth,</hi> and is as <hi>Active for his Church and Saints</hi> Above, as Below, while on <hi>Earth;</hi> ſo far as is neceſſary, till he brings forth all his <hi>Saints</hi> Appearing alſo in the <hi>Glory of his Melchiſedechia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prieſthood,</hi> as <hi>Kings and Prieſts</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>But to Return to the <hi>Prophecy, Revel.</hi> 20. I obſerve, as I have already obſerved, There is not only the Shell or Words, but the Deep Reaſon of <hi>Things;</hi> as All <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and moſt particularly all the Lines of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> before it, Run into It, and Center in it; and All Require ſuch a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> of ſuch a State; of <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and <hi>New Earth;</hi> and of a <hi>Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Time,</hi> that may ſpeak <hi>Perfection,</hi> to <hi>Accompliſh Them.</hi> And that <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> this <hi>Prophecy</hi> Declares to be a <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> and then All to be Drawn up into <hi>Eternity,</hi> and no otherwiſe to End.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argum.</hi> 5. The Obſervation upon the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> I made hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in my <hi>Patriarchal Line, p.</hi> 58. does much ſway my Judgment ſtill concerning the <hi>Thouſand Years Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> viz. <q rend="inline">By the Recollection of each <hi>Patriarch's Life,</hi> whol, and together, is moſt Pompouſly ſet out; That none of theſe <hi>Holy Men</hi> Attain'd a Full <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> of Life, though ſome Lifes ſwell'd ſo much above <hi>Nine hundred,</hi> as if they would mount to a <hi>Thouſand;</hi> yet it was ſaid to Them, <hi>Hitherto ſhall you come, and no further,</hi> for a <hi>Thouſand</hi> in <hi>Sacred Record</hi> is a <hi>Number of Perfection,</hi> that is not Allowed to any <hi>Years</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> in <hi>Adam</hi>'s <hi>Apoſtate State,</hi> but Reſerv'd for the <hi>Reſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Second Adam;</hi> and <hi>p.</hi> 165. As if the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> were a <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> Guarded with <hi>Cherubims,</hi> that none might Take of it; <hi>Enoch</hi> had a particular Exemption of not <hi>Dying;</hi> yet no One might be in a Viſible State on Earth One Thouſand Years;</q> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I am Confirm'd by Reading, what Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> ſo Reverend, ſo Learned, ſo Conſidering, and ſo far from what is call'd <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> as every One knows, hath written, in his Excellent and Generally Accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Practical Diſcourſe of Death,</hi> p. 129, 130. Wherein it is moſt Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, that he Writes not, as having Eſpous'd the Opinion of the <hi>Thouſand Years Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> nor was Intentionally Writing upon it, But ſo Diſcerning and Quick-ſighted a Perſon was ſtruck with its <hi>Beams of Light and Truth,</hi> while he was upon another View; And thus he Writes: <q rend="inline">The longeſt Term of <hi>Humane Life,</hi> after the <hi>Sentence of Death</hi> paſſed on <hi>Man,</hi> was a <hi>Thouſand Years.</hi> And Comparing this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation with that Promiſe of a <hi>Thouſand Years Reign with Chriſt,</hi> which is call'd the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> and is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Portion only of <hi>Martyrs</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97298:12"/> 
                  <hi>Confeſſors,</hi> and <hi>pure and ſincere Chriſtians,</hi> Revel. 20. I have been apt to Conclude, To live a <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> is the Priviledge only of <hi>Immortal Creatures;</hi> That if <hi>Adam</hi> had continued <hi>Innocent,</hi> he ſhould have liv'd no longer upon <hi>Earth,</hi> but have been Tranſlated to <hi>Heaven</hi> without <hi>Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> For this <hi>Thouſand Years Reign of the Saints with Chriſt,</hi> whatever that Signifies, ſeems to be Intended as a <hi>Reparation of Death,</hi> which They fall under by <hi>Adam</hi>'s <hi>Sin:</hi> But then theſe <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> do not put an End to the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of thoſe <hi>Glorious Saints,</hi> but they are <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Creatures;</hi> And though this <hi>Reign with Chriſt</hi> continues but a <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years,</hi> Their <hi>Happineſs</hi> ſhall have no End, though the <hi>Scene</hi> may change and vary, for over ſuch the <hi>Second Death ſhall have no power.</hi> Or elſe this <hi>Thouſand Years Reign with Chriſt</hi> muſt ſignifie an <hi>Eternal,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeable Kingdom,</hi> a <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> being a certain <hi>Earneſt</hi> of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality;</hi> But there is an Unanſwerable <hi>Objection</hi> againſt that, Becauſe we read of the <hi>Expiring of thoſe Thouſand Years,</hi> and what ſhall come af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, even the <hi>Final Judgment of all the World.</hi> This is a <hi>Great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,</hi> which we muſt not hope perfectly to Underſtand, till we ſee the <hi>Bleſſed Accompliſhment</hi> of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I could not but Tranſcribe a <hi>Paragraph</hi> worthy of <hi>Letters of Gold;</hi> Not becauſe ſuitable to my Senſe, of ſmall Account; but becauſe ſo Agreeable with <hi>Senſe of Scripture,</hi> if I can be ſure I <hi>ſee,</hi> or <hi>know</hi> any Thing; And yet how little <hi>taken notice of?</hi> To conclude the <hi>Argument,</hi> The <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are made by <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Emblem</hi> and <hi>Hierogliphick</hi> of the <hi>Perfection of Time,</hi> and do litterally expreſs that very <hi>Time,</hi> God hath Ordain'd to be the <hi>Fulneſs of Time,</hi> and the <hi>Perfection of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the <hi>Third Thing</hi> propos'd, to conſider any other <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis</hi> or <hi>Model</hi> of Things in Bar of this propos'd; And I find theſe Two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That All this <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> with its <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> are ſuppos'd rather to Fit the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity;</hi> Againſt this I Argue.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. <hi>v.</hi> 1. are certainly the very ſame that <hi>Fly away</hi> from the <hi>pure Cryſtal Throne of Eternity,</hi> and from his <hi>Face</hi> that <hi>Sate upon it,</hi> Ready to <hi>Deliver up the Kingdom to God All in All.</hi> This is certain, becauſe the <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> are Concurrent with the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> as is moſt Clear, by the Conjunct <hi>Viſion John</hi> had of Them, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. 12. <hi>I ſaw a New Heaven;</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>And I</hi> John <hi>ſaw the holy City.</hi> When he <hi>Saw the New Heaven, &amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> The <hi>firſt Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>first Earth were paſſed away.</hi> So then the <hi>Heaven and Earth,</hi> that were with the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> were not the <hi>firſt Heaven and Earth,</hi> but the <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi> that were at the ſame time with the <hi>Holy City; And they fled away,</hi> as is moſt Evident by the cloſe Connexion and Order between the <hi>Compaſſing the Holy and Beloved City,</hi> which cannot be ſuppos'd to be any other, then the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> call'd by the Name of the <hi>Holy City,</hi> as <hi>c.</hi> 20. 9. ſo <hi>c.</hi> 21. 2. and the <hi>Beloved City,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Bride.</hi> For after that Aſſault that was after
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97298:12"/> the 1000 <hi>Y. Satan was caſt into the Lake,</hi> that had the <hi>Power of Death;</hi> And then immediately the <hi>White Throne was ſeen,</hi> and <hi>Heaven and Earth fled away,</hi> which muſt be the <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi> Cotemporary with the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſo with the 1000 <hi>Years;</hi> and ſeeing, as was ſaid juſt now, They muſt be <hi>new Heaven,</hi> and <hi>New Earth;</hi> Therefore the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and <hi>New Earth</hi> continue not to Eternity.</p>
            <p>For I cannot ſee where there can be any Doubt in the Connexion, or Order, the <hi>Divine Prophecy</hi> hath ſo taken care; <hi>Sathans caſting into the Lake</hi> muſt needs be after the 1000 Years, therefore after the <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth;</hi> the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> that <hi>Fled,</hi> muſt be Thoſe that were at the <hi>Judging,</hi> and <hi>caſting the Dead into the Lake;</hi> Can we ſuppoſe then, that this <hi>White Throne,</hi> the <hi>Judging the Dead,</hi> and <hi>caſting the Dead into the Lake,</hi> was before the 1000 Years, and ſo the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth flying</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; and then indeed They muſt be the <hi>Firſt Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Firſt Earth,</hi> and not the <hi>New Ones:</hi> But All that cannot be, becauſe whatever was not <hi>Written in the Book of Life,</hi> was then <hi>caſt into the Lake;</hi> And it is certain, <hi>Sathan</hi> was not <hi>Written in the Book of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe;</hi> therefore he Could not be <hi>out of the Lake</hi> at the Time of <hi>Death,</hi> and the <hi>Dead</hi> being <hi>caſt into the Lake;</hi> But he was not <hi>caſt into the Lake,</hi> till the 1000 Years were paſt; So that this whole Tranſaction upon <hi>Death,</hi> and the <hi>Flying of Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> were all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the 1000 Years, and therefore the <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> which Run along with the 1000 Years, were the <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> that <hi>Fled away,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which was the Thing to be ſhown, and is ſhown: For if ſuch a <hi>Connexion,</hi> as this will not prove, nothing can be prov'd by Conſequence from Scripture.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe Three Expreſſions of the Apoſtle, The <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall be <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd up by the Son, The Son ſhall be ſubject, God ſhall be All in All;</hi> ſo ſtrongly ſway with me, that no diſtinction of Acquiſition and Fruition can weigh againſt them; but that ſuch a State, as of the <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> and a <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> proportionate to it, cannot be the State of the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity;</hi> Eſpecially when I Joyn to it, thoſe Words of our Lords <hi>Mediatory Prayer, John</hi> 17. That <hi>They may be one in us,</hi> and that <hi>They may ſee my Glory;</hi> and that <hi>Glory</hi> was the <hi>Glory</hi> Chriſt <hi>had with the Father before the Foundation of the World;</hi> So that the <hi>Glory</hi> of the Humane Nature of Chriſt, and of the <hi>Elect Angels,</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> being firſt confeſs'd; All the State of <hi>Glory</hi> is Brought to the neareſt, that can be, to that State of <hi>Glory, before the World began,</hi> and ſo not of <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth,</hi> and what is Agreeable to the Creation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A <hi>Delivery up</hi> of the <hi>Glory of the Judiciary Kingdom,</hi> or of that proper to the <hi>Day of Judgment, to the Father,</hi> and the <hi>Son's being ſubject,</hi> that is, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down that Luſtre of Appearance, proper to that Adminiſtration, cannot be denied; And that, and no other, which is always Attributed to the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> and to the <hi>Man Christ Jeſus,</hi> and the <hi>delivering</hi> up that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and no other, is what I plead for; and no otherwiſe, then ſo far, as is neceſſary for the making Good of what the Apoſtle hath ſaid;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97298:13"/> That the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is to be <hi>deliver'd up,</hi> that the <hi>Son is to be ſubject,</hi> and <hi>God; to be All in All:</hi> From which, as having ſome Higher, Deeper, and more Subſtantial Senſe, then the diſtinction of Acquiſition, and Fruition, can Comprehend, I cannot depart.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The Superlative unexpreſſible Excellency of the <hi>Divine Glory</hi> from <hi>Eternity,</hi> hath ſo Great a Command upon my Underſtanding, together with that Expreſſion of the Apoſtles of <hi>God's being All in All,</hi> that altho the Humane Nature of Chriſt, as united to the Divine; though the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature of Chriſt and his Saints; the Union of Saints to God by Chriſt, be Free, and wholly <hi>Grace;</hi> and were not indeed from Eternity; yet Joyning the ſo often mention'd Aſſertion of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> with our <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Glory, before the World began,</hi> Aſſures me; that the State of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> is Brought to the higheſt Nearneſs Created, Nature is capable of, to that <hi>Glory,</hi> before the <hi>Foundation of the World,</hi> even as the Humane Nature of Chriſt is ſo Advanc'd; and that that Objectition, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Humane Nature of Chriſt had not an Exiſtence in that <hi>Glory,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World, Argues to me the more ſtrongly, that All this is ſo; For it ſpeaks that Humane Nature it ſelf, therefore drawn more out of all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Glory,</hi> into the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> and that the Divine Nature of the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> is our Object, and not the Humane Nature of Chriſt; all the objective <hi>Glory</hi> of Chriſt in his Humane Nature, and of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> being ſeen in <hi>Speculo Divinitatis,</hi> in that Infinite Mirrour of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature; And herein I Relye on the very Words of Scripture, that cannot be over-rul'd: And ſeeing God hath been pleas'd to make the Humane Nature of Chriſt, and the Union of his <hi>Saints</hi> to himſelf Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, as himſelf; (So far am I from ſuppoſing a Fall from that State) the Exaltation of them to Cloſeſt Approximation to that <hi>Glory to Eternity,</hi> that was from <hi>Eternity,</hi> is the Ceſſation of <hi>Oeconomy,</hi> and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Eternal State; wherein the <hi>Saints are Equal to Angels,</hi> and need them not for their Enjoyment, but as All meet in God: On the contrary, though <hi>Devils,</hi> and <hi>Loſt Spirits</hi> have all the Senſe, and Action Agreeable to their <hi>Lost State,</hi> Yet it is not ſuch kind of Hoſtile Action, as now They are Exercis'd in, but are in as perfect a State of Suffering, as, and above All we can conceive, and ſo for ever, and in the moſt Unchangeable Miſery.</p>
            <p>And whereas a Political Conception of the <hi>Eternal King,</hi> his Laws and Subjects, ſeems to Require Another State, or order then this, I Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert: Yet as from Eternity, Supreme Dominion was Eſſential to God, even as Mercy, Goodneſs, Truth, before any Subjects, capable to Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe them upon; So to <hi>Eternity,</hi> without any ſuch Adminiſtration, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Political Laws we Apprehend, and have known here. But who can ſail in this Infinite Ocean now, without the having All Thought and Underſtanding, Loſt in that Infinity! But this is certain, God is a <hi>King Eternal,</hi> as well as <hi>Immortal, Inviſible,</hi> and the <hi>Only Wiſe God, To Him therefore be Glory be for ever:</hi> And in All this I moſt humbly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97298:13"/> Acknowledge Jeſus Chriſt, God and Man, the Mediator, even the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator of this union to Eternity; But the very Nature of a Mediator is not, that he ſhould be Our utmoſt Objective Reſt, but that, as All Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks, He ſhould <hi>Bring us to God,</hi> even <hi>God All in All</hi> by ſeveral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, the Higheſt of which is his own <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and at laſt to the moſt Immediate union in and by Himſelf, which is the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I have endeavour'd to make plain, that the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> as in the <hi>Judgment Given to Him,</hi> as the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> enſtated in a <hi>World to come</hi> of <hi>New Heavens</hi> and a <hi>New Earth</hi> does not Laſt for ever; but is, as in our Law, a Leaſe for a Year, to put into Poſſeſſion, that the Eternal Inheritance may veſt in us: I come in the Laſt place to Clear my <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis</hi> in theſe Great Points from the Suppoſition, that there may be other <hi>Worlds</hi> beſides the <hi>World</hi> preſent, that is now near 6000 Years old, and that <hi>World to come</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> whereof I Speak, and then the whole <hi>deliver'd up to God All in All;</hi> either as <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Bodies in union to Him; or as <hi>Loſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pirits,</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi> in Bodies, ſo <hi>Subdued</hi> quite below under his <hi>Kingdom</hi> in the <hi>Lake,</hi> as to be Eternally ſeparated from him.</p>
            <p>Now I Briefly Argue againſt any other Worlds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. Becauſe the Scripture in All, it ſays, Stints our Thoughts, and Imaginations in this variety of Worlds, Riſing and Repullulating, as it were out of the <hi>Firſt World,</hi> that we Read of the Creation of <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. An Extent of Thought beyond this, Brings us under a <hi>Vertigo,</hi> a Giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Apprehenſion, that we know not where we are, and Inclines to <hi>Scepticiſm,</hi> a doubt of All Things; and if we do not ſtop to <hi>Atheiſtick</hi> Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pitions, Running out of the Aſſurance of the Truth of All Religion; and of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe Scripture Repreſents the <hi>Angels,</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> of both the Saved, and of the Loſt, as ſo many, and thoſe in ſuch a variety. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> never ſinning, but Elect, and Confirm'd in Original Holineſs; <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> Falling, and never Recover'd; M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Created in Original Purity, Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; and a number very vaſt in it ſelf Recover'd; ſome dying, but vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated from Death by the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> Others in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> that though they might fall and die, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>living remaining,</hi> are yet ſecur'd by the Mediator; and the Loſt of Mankind, <hi>Fallen from their Firſt Eſtate,</hi> and not Recover'd, notwithſtanding the Grace of the Mediator, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Every-where alſo Magnifies the <hi>Riches</hi> and <hi>Fullneſs,</hi> the Variety of the <hi>Creation,</hi> as declaring to the utmoſt the Glory of God, that He thinks fit to Reveal in ſuch away, eſpecially as it ſhall be in Chriſt's <hi>World to Come.</hi> Now the Infinite Riches of the Divine Being, ſhewing it ſelf in ſo Great an Explication of its own ſo <hi>Variegated Wiſdom, Epheſ.</hi> 3. 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to <hi>Principalities,</hi> and <hi>Powers</hi> in <hi>Heavenly Places,</hi> in and by the Church, when it is carried through all <hi>Oeconomies,</hi> eſpecially that in the <hi>Fullneſs of Times,</hi> (wherein <hi>Angels</hi> Themſelves ſhall be Recapitulated, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 10.) into the <hi>Eternal Kingdom,</hi> is All, Scripture Reveals; and it carries our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97298:14"/> Thoughts not a Moment beyond, but winds up all herein; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Search beyond it, looks like the <hi>vain Puff and Swolneſs of a fleſhly Mind,</hi> as not being <hi>wiſe</hi> to <hi>Sobriety,</hi> but above <hi>what is written.</hi> And yet I know the <hi>Infinite Being,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Power of God,</hi> before ſome <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> and ſo <hi>Zealous of the Glory of God,</hi> may cauſe them to ſay, <hi>Who knows what God will do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Becauſe it is not only unconceivable, but directly againſt the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogy</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> That there ſhould be any <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Creatures In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual,</hi> or <hi>Animal,</hi> or according to the <hi>Mechaniſm</hi> and <hi>Frame</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> but what is <hi>All in Jeſus Chriſt the eternal Word in our Nature.</hi> Now how is it Conceivable either in <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi> He ſhould be Related to Another, or any more Worlds, as to this? wherein he was <hi>made Man, the Son of Abraham, the Son of David.</hi> Can there be any more <hi>Sons of Abraham,</hi> or of <hi>David?</hi> Can the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> Aſſume any more or other Created Nature into Himſelf? He muſt then ſee a World, or Worlds, wherein He hath no Intereſt, as in that Perſonality, wherein we Believe Him according to Scripture; This would be a Diminution to his <hi>Glory;</hi> Therefore this is to me a moſt <hi>Concluſive Argument</hi> againſt any Worlds before or after this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. I add, the Manifeſtations of the <hi>Grace of God in Chriſt,</hi> even the <hi>Riches of Glory</hi> on the <hi>Veſſels of Mercy</hi> prepared to <hi>Glory and Honour,</hi> and of his <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> on the <hi>Veſſels of Wrath,</hi> and unto <hi>Diſhonour,</hi> are to the Heighth, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſhews, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9 22. Any more then would ſpeak the Imperfection of what hath been, is, and is to be; which no way agrees with <hi>Scripture,</hi> manifeſting all to the utmoſt. From whence I conclude, ſuch a Suppoſal of more Worlds cannot Rationally Barr the <hi>Hipotheſis</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as <hi>God All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I have endeavoured ſo to ſtate <hi>that Kingdom</hi> of the 1000 <hi>Y.</hi> wherein not only his Enemies are <hi>in Fieri,</hi> or about, as they ſpeak, to be <hi>ſubdued,</hi> but it ſhall be brought to that <hi>Conſummation</hi> and <hi>Perfection,</hi> which the <hi>Apostle</hi> ſpeaks of, and which is the very Character of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> Heb 2. 1. <hi>That all Things ſhould be ſo put under Him,</hi> there ſhould be nothing left, that is not put under Him. <hi>But now we ſee not All Things ſo put under Him;</hi> by which we know, the <hi>Time of his Kingdom is not yet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There may yet be remaining many Spinoſe and Snarl'd <hi>Queſtions,</hi> the Anſwering of which would ſtill beget more, and make Controverſies as <hi>endleſs</hi> as the <hi>Genealogies</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks of; I therefore deſignedly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear Them. I know the Like may be drawn over the moſt <hi>Fundamental Principles of Theology</hi> by a diſpos'd <hi>Questioniſt,</hi> as is very plain by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel I have given betwixt that ſo Acknowledged One of the <hi>Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the <hi>Thouſand Years Kingdom,</hi> liable to the very ſame Captious Enquiries.</p>
            <p>I will therefore wave any further Regard to thoſe <hi>Perplexing Queſtions,</hi> with Tranſcribing ſome few <hi>Obſervations</hi> out of that moſt <hi>Satisfying Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally Honourable</hi> Mr <hi>Boyl,</hi> in his <hi>Appendix</hi> to the ſo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97298:14"/> 
               <hi>Graceful Pourtracture</hi> of the <hi>Christian Vertuoſo,</hi> of which he is Himſelf the <hi>Life;</hi> It is his <hi>Reflections</hi> upon the Diſtinction of <hi>Above,</hi> and not <hi>against Reaſon,</hi> viz. <hi>pag.</hi> 6. <hi>parag.</hi> 7. <q rend="inline">There are divers Truths in <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> that <hi>Reaſon</hi> left to it ſelf, would never have found out, nor ſo much perhaps as Dream'd of; (and ſuch undoubtedly is the <hi>Thouſand Years Kingdom of Chriſt.)</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>parag.</hi> 10. There are <hi>Truths</hi> ſo Abſtruſe, that when They are propos'd, as clearly, as proper unambiguous Terms can propoſe Them, They do nevertheleſs ſurpaſs our Dim and Bounded <hi>Reaſon.</hi> And ſuch alſo are many Things concerning this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt;</hi> There are many Things in General, and in determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Conceptions, (as that <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> moſt preſſingly Inſtances) Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Time, Place, Local Motion, Quantity;</hi> wherein though we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand One Another when we ſpeak of Them, yet if we throughly look into Them, there are ſuch <hi>Difficulties</hi> as oppreſs our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and wherein the Men, who make ſuch ſhrewd Objections againſt our <hi>Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis,</hi> will hardly be able to pitch on any that will not Allow us to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay them in the ſame Coyn.</q> So alſo are there in the <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> much more in theſe of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> and yet none are therefore to be Rejected. That alſo is Greatly Conſiderable to the Preſent Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>pa.</hi> 6. <hi>parag.</hi> 8. <q rend="inline">There are many <hi>Truths,</hi> and more then we are wont to Imagine; that we want <hi>Mediums</hi> or <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to Diſcover; that if They were clearly propos'd, would be Intelligible to us, even as <hi>Celeſtial Lights</hi> in thoſe Ineſtimably Remote <hi>Regions,</hi> for want of more Reaching <hi>Teleſcopes.</hi>
               </q> Theſe, and many more <hi>moſt excellent Obſervations,</hi> in that <hi>ſhort,</hi> but <hi>Maſſie Treatiſe,</hi> if well Conſider'd, would Reconcile our <hi>Thoughts</hi> to the <hi>Glorious Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> however hitherto Dark in the Main; and many Things relating to the <hi>Modus</hi> or <hi>Circumſtance,</hi> more Dark; But I make no doubt, thoſe Reaching, Commanding <hi>Teleſcopes</hi> will be brought forth fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Uſe ere-long, by the <hi>Everlasting Gospel preach'd;</hi> when what was <hi>Myſtery</hi> before, will be no longer ſo; Even as what was ſo in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> became no longer ſo, by the <hi>New</hi> Revealing it; as the ſame <hi>Honourable Writer</hi> Remarks. In the mean time, how Noble would it be in a <hi>Royal Society</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Vertuoſo's</hi> to call for, Encourage, and Receive all <hi>Propoſes</hi> concerning <hi>Prophecy,</hi> its <hi>Line of Time,</hi> and the <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling</hi> of it! That would bring ſo Adorable a part of <hi>Theology</hi> into <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentality,</hi> to the Great Honour of the <hi>Age.</hi> But if neither <hi>Divines,</hi> nor <hi>Vertuoſo's</hi> will do it, God will ſuddenly Grant a New Charter for a <hi>Royal Society</hi> of <hi>Vertuoſo's</hi> for his <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> willingly alſo forbear the ſaying any more concerning the <hi>Calling of the Jews;</hi> the very Occaſion given to deny it, being in the Senſe of moſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> a kind of Invidious Thing: I only ſay, the <hi>Jews</hi> according to all <hi>Prophecy,</hi> being kept in publick View, as a Deſolated and Obſtinate Unbelieving People, make it very Believable; They are pteſerved to ſuch a <hi>Gracious purpoſe;</hi> Wherein it is moſt True, <hi>Inſinite Power and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> hath Engag'd it Self, in Anſwer to the <hi>hardeſt Objections,</hi> according
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97298:15"/> to <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s <hi>Reſolve</hi> of that Queſtion; <hi>Can theſe Dead Bones live? O Lord God, thou knoweſt,</hi> Ezek. 37. 3. And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s <hi>Theorem,</hi> concerning the Caſe; <hi>God is able to graft Them in,</hi> Rom. 11. 23.</p>
            <p>I am alſo willing to Accept that <hi>Reſerve</hi> for taking in <hi>Papal Rome</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Apocalyptick Prophecy;</hi> That as <hi>Pagan Rome</hi> was moſt certainly in its Time, ſo <hi>Papal Rome</hi> may be <hi>Babylon</hi> alſo: Only I cannot but Obſerve, that the <hi>Caſſandrianiſm</hi> and <hi>Grotianiſm,</hi> of Suppoſiting <hi>Pagan Rome</hi> to all the <hi>Prophecy of the Revelation,</hi> wherein the <hi>Learned,</hi> and according to his own <hi>Sentiments,</hi> moſt <hi>Pious Dr. Hammond,</hi> Joyn'd through the <hi>Antiperiſtatick Paroxiſm,</hi> He carried to the Times He Lived in; (and againſt which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath Written in General.) This ſure is much more Obnoxious then the Agreeing with <hi>Conformiſts,</hi> concerning any <hi>Apocalyptick Notions;</hi> For it Argues much more a <hi>Divine Impreſſion,</hi> when Any are carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, then down a Stream; eſpecially in Favour of a <hi>Prophecy,</hi> that will as certainly Take down the <hi>Grandieur,</hi> and <hi>Antiquate</hi> the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of moſt of the Conſtitution, They Favour, within a ſhort time, as even the <hi>Papal</hi> it ſelf; Let it be ſpoken without the Disfavour of many Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefiled Names of Sardis:</hi> The moſt Sagacious of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> ſo much underſtood an <hi>Antichriſtian Rome,</hi> Revel. 17. That to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the <hi>Blow,</hi> They, as <hi>Balam</hi> and <hi>Chaiaphas</hi> have <hi>Propheſied</hi> of an <hi>Anti-Chriſt</hi> that ſhall yet come to Deſtroy <hi>Rome,</hi> and its <hi>Pſeudo-Catholick State.</hi> And they are thus far in the Right of it: That as the <hi>Papal State</hi> is the <hi>Antichriſt</hi> to the <hi>True Christ;</hi> So the <hi>True Chriſt's</hi> Coming will be <hi>Antichriſt</hi> indeed to that <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Christ</hi> direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite to Him, and that will come into his Room, and ſo even per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly bring Him to nothing with the <hi>Brightneſs of his own Appearance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſſing then from all theſe Things, I come to what Remains of Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Moment, and that is, Concerning the <hi>Churches</hi> in General; more Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> and <hi>Laodicea,</hi> and moſt eſpecially of <hi>Laodicea;</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I muſt acknowledge the moſt Difficult and Hardlieſt to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd Hinge of my <hi>Hipotheſis</hi> Turns.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I firſt therefore conſider, what concerns the <hi>Seven Churches</hi> in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and that is, with Relation to the <hi>Angels of the Churches;</hi> Concerning which, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Reply;</hi> thus Writes, <hi>p.</hi> 14. <q rend="inline">For my part <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> If I Believed, that by God's Inſtitution, the <hi>Church Catholick</hi> muſt have One Univerſal <hi>Humane Angel,</hi> or <hi>Government, Monarchical,</hi> or <hi>Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical,</hi> or mixt; I would preſently be a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> But he had ſaid before; What is the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of <hi>Papacy,</hi> but the Claim of an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Power</hi> over the <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Pope,</hi> or his <hi>Council,</hi> He being the Head</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now in this I would earneſtly Beg the ſame Candor of Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in all I have Written, that in this matter I would Uſe; that is, To ſeek out the beſt and faireſt Senſe that I could poſſibly find, wherein I had any Reaſon of Check at what is Written; ſhould I be ſo unjuſt, as to underſtand by Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s being a <hi>Papiſt</hi> preſently, on ſuch Terms, any Thing elſe, but that as to that Point of Acnowledging the <hi>Pope</hi> as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97298:15"/> 
               <hi>Head of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> as they ſpeak, He would be a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> and only upon the Suppoſition of <hi>Divine Inſtitution,</hi> and that the <hi>Eſſence of Popery</hi> conſiſted in that; whereas to be a <hi>Papiſt</hi> is generally underſtood to be an Embracer of all the <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Superſtitions, &amp;c.</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> hath eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> which is ſuppos'd to be in Him, to eſtabliſh what he pleaſes, as He is ſuch a <hi>Head.</hi> Should I Turn this every way to Aggravate it, and Raiſe <hi>Tragical Suspitions</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> upon it? Far be it from me; I take his Meaning ſimply, as He intended it: It is but the ſame Meaſure, I deſire.</p>
            <p>But I come to the main Point, and thereunto I make Anſwer in theſe following Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the <hi>Churches,</hi> I do not underſtand ſo the <hi>Symbolized <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,</hi> as that the particular <hi>Churches</hi> named, ſhould be Excluded; but each <hi>Church</hi> with its <hi>Paſtors</hi> Included: So that ſuppoſing a <hi>Proeſto's</hi> to be underſtood by the <hi>Angel;</hi> It would Ariſe to no more, then that all theſe <hi>Seven Succeſſions</hi> through the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church</hi> were Repreſented in each <hi>Succeſſion</hi> by theſe ſingle <hi>Churches,</hi> and their <hi>Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I am very far from Thinking, that either <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or ſo much as a <hi>Proesto's</hi> is underſtood by <hi>Angel;</hi> but that <hi>Angel</hi> throughout this <hi>Prophecy</hi> Generally, (I do not ſay in every Particular) Signifies a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective Miniſtery of <hi>ſit Instruments</hi> to every Purpoſe; and ſo <hi>Angels of the Churches</hi> Intends the <hi>Holy Paſtors</hi> or <hi>Miniſters</hi> of each <hi>Succeſſional State of the Church,</hi> who were Inſtructed in the Main Concernments of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in each <hi>Age,</hi> and Remonſtrated them to the <hi>Churches.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I obſerve a Care, as I Apprehend, of the <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> Foreprizing any ſuch Interpretation of the <hi>Angels,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if They were ſingle Perſons; For ſaith Chriſt, Chapter 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. <hi>The Seven Stars are the Angels of the Seven Churches; Seven</hi> is applyed to the <hi>Stars,</hi> and to the <hi>Churches,</hi> but not to the <hi>Angels,</hi> as it were Declining the Application of the Number to the <hi>Angels,</hi> the neareſt and moſt immediate <hi>Symbol,</hi> of what-ever was intended, that there might be no Collection; They were ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I obſerve ſuch a <hi>Sympathy</hi> between the <hi>Angels of the Churches,</hi> and the <hi>Churches,</hi> that in one Great Inſtance the <hi>Spirit</hi> turns off from the <hi>Angel</hi> to ſpeak to the <hi>Body of the Church:</hi> To <hi>You I ſay, and to the Reſt of Thyatyra,</hi> Chap 2. <hi>v.</hi> 24, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. And that is a <hi>Key</hi> to the <hi>Intention</hi> in every <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Churches;</hi> Beſides the <hi>Book,</hi> of what <hi>John</hi> ſaw, to be <hi>Written</hi> by <hi>Him,</hi> Chap. 1. <hi>v.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. is directed to each <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Chriſt's</hi> eſpecial Command; and to the <hi>Angels,</hi> only as <hi>Speakers</hi> or <hi>Prolocutors,</hi> as to our <hi>Speakers</hi> in <hi>Parliament;</hi> and it is ſtill ſaid, <hi>He that hath an Ear, let him hear what the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſaith to the Churches;</hi> And the Promiſes are made to each ſingle Perſon of <hi>each Church;</hi> ſo that what is ſaid to any One, is ſaid to All; wherefore as to me it is moſt plain, All <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Power,</hi> any further than it holds out the <hi>Word of Chriſt,</hi> which every ſingle Chriſtian is to know for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo to ſubmit unto, is no other than ſome Vein, at leaſt of the <hi>Feet of Clay;</hi> much more when it Takes upon it to be Sirly, or Lordly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97298:16"/> over Conſciences; and moſt of All, when to Enforce it ſelf; It pleads, by <hi>Law Eſtabliſhed.</hi> So far am I in my own Judgment from being Guilty in this matter of an <hi>Over-zeal</hi> ſupported only by Ignorance, or not <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Knowledge,</hi> that I was always aware, and Guarded againſt this Conſequence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I come in the Second place to Apply my Thoughts to <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> and <hi>Laodicea,</hi> as Churches of Another World, which that They ſhould be, none of the <hi>Aſian Churches,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians</hi> for 1500 Years ever Believ'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. This I look upon, as not Known to us, what was Believ'd in the Time neareſt to the Giving that <hi>Prophecy.</hi> Since then, Gradually a <hi>Horror of Darkneſs</hi> came upon the <hi>Churches,</hi> eſpecially, as to the <hi>Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyptical Prophecy,</hi> and moſt eſpecially, as to the Retir'd parts of it; And Ah las, how much doth it ſtill Remain? This I look upon then, as ſo Little of an Argument againſt their being ſo, that I paſs from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Each Epiſtle is writ, not ſo to the Churches of the Future World, but that They are for the <hi>Learning,</hi> and <hi>Admonition</hi> of every Age of the <hi>Church</hi> in their moſt <hi>Myſtic</hi> Senſe, (if <hi>They had Ears to hear,</hi> which very words ſhew the Senſe to be highly <hi>Parabolick,</hi> and <hi>Myſtic)</hi> and ſtill much more in their plain Doctrinal, Inſtructing or Reproving, Correcting, Conſolatory Senſe, and directed to all <hi>Churches,</hi> and <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in all Ages ſince; Even as They were for the <hi>Churches</hi> of that Time, and more particularly, Written, Each Epiſtle, to the <hi>Church</hi> then, to which each was directed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to the Church of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> and the Objections concerning it, I have ſo Fully ſpoken in my Treatiſe of the <hi>Reformation to be Reform'd;</hi> eſpecially at Page 62. <hi>&amp;c</hi> that I would only Recollect this Brief Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: That I look upon ſome Low, and Depreſs'd State of <hi>Saints</hi> of Chriſt, Symboll'd all along by it from the <hi>Reformation</hi> Entring, until the <hi>Reformation</hi> it ſelf ſhall be <hi>Reform'd;</hi> to which the <hi>Little ſtrength,</hi> and ſuch like Expreſſions are to be Applied; That it is ſo Long, Over-Lour'd by the Height and Grandieur of <hi>Sardis,</hi> eſpecially thoſe of it, who make <hi>Them of the Synagogue of Sathan;</hi> That it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nters its proper Time of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, when it ſhall Appear in Another Kind of Glory at 97; when alſo the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> enters its Succeſſion at the end of the Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and the Time of it, as I have always explain'd that Succeſſion. Then Chriſt hath Right of a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the Four <hi>Monarchies</hi> being at an end, and prepares for its Glory by the <hi>Seven Thunders opened,</hi> and the <hi>Vials poured out,</hi> wherein the Church of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> ſhall be Highly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable; This State laſts for <hi>Daniel's</hi> 75, Added to 1260 of the Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and making 1335, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 12, 13. ſhall be at our 1772. Then the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> comes down on the <hi>Philadelphian Church,</hi> in a Glory Tranſcenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to he Church States that ever have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th;</hi> for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he end of the 1000 Years, the Glory Retires fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>on Earth,</hi> This <hi>Looſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sathan,</hi> and the Condemn'd, Captiva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>og</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> to make whatever Attempt They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ility o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97298:16"/> Change in the State of the <hi>Saints of the firſt Reſurrection Above;</hi> but on the <hi>Saints Below,</hi> it hath the Operation of the Abatement of the <hi>former Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors</hi> of <hi>Bringing all their Glory to the Jeruſalem Above,</hi> and <hi>Earneſt Deſire of being Caught up to it,</hi> as its intended; but are about to <hi>Acquieſce</hi> and <hi>Settle</hi> in a <hi>State by Themſelves on Earth;</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> by no means Allows, nor Endures. Here enters the <hi>Laodicean State;</hi> of which becauſe I have, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver at any Largeneſs, publiſhed my <hi>Thoughts,</hi> I would be more large, when I have given theſe <hi>Pre-Cautions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That neither on my Judgment concerning <hi>Laodicea,</hi> nor concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> as the Captivated Dead or Condemn'd of the <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years</hi> do <hi>I</hi> ſuſpend the Weight of my <hi>principal Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> but therein offer the <hi>beſt Light, I</hi> am able to give in ſo <hi>dark Points,</hi> in Agreement with my <hi>principal Doctrine,</hi> and the <hi>Symmetry</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and Commend my Self therein to the Candor of the Wiſe and Sober, without any occaſion of Offence or Exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the <hi>ſtrangeneſs</hi> of the <hi>Abatement</hi> of <hi>Fervours</hi> in the <hi>Living Saints,</hi> or the <hi>Laodicean Church,</hi> will be eaſily taken off by conſidering; The Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of the <hi>beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reated State,</hi> depends upon the <hi>Degrees of Divine Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> which does not perfect it ſelf into the very Nature of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs,</hi> but in the <hi>Kingdom of the New Jeruſalem Above,</hi> and in the <hi>Kingdom of Glory;</hi> Yet from hence no ſuch Thing as a <hi>Falling from Grace</hi> in the <hi>Saints</hi> much leſs in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> though Below, can be Fairly Collected.</p>
            <p>For there is an unchangeable Love manifeſting it ſelf in the midſt of We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kneſs, till th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Saints</hi> are brought to the State of <hi>Incorruption</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality;</hi> which is not but in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt Above;</hi> where the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection</hi> are, and the <hi>Living Remaining,</hi> are (as I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Aſſerted) <hi>Cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht up</hi> without the loſs of any One, and ſo <hi>Deliver'd up together</hi> into the <hi>Abſolute Eternal Life of God All in All;</hi> which <hi>States</hi> are by the <hi>Decree of God</hi> in their <hi>own Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re,</hi> ſo Fram'd by <hi>Infinite Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> in Conjunction with <hi>Infinite Love and Grace in Chriſt,</hi> as Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, as <hi>God himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Manifeſtation therefore of the Weakneſs of any State, but of that Abſolute <hi>Incorruption</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt Above,</hi> and of <hi>Eternity;</hi> for the Manifeſtation of the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>Christ's</hi> bringing his <hi>Saints</hi> Below, ſafe to theſe States through the poſſibility of Danger at the end of the <hi>Thouſand Years;</hi> for the Greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onqueſt over <hi>Satan, Sin,</hi> and <hi>Death;</hi> And laſtly, for the ſhewing the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of putting an <hi>End</hi> to all <hi>Church-State on Earth,</hi> without ſuch a <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> coming down upon it; which <hi>Infinite Wiſdom,</hi> for the <hi>Glory of God All in All,</hi> had Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd to be only a <hi>Thouſand Years;</hi> On all theſe Accounts there is a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Appearance of the Danger; but it was no ſooner given Leave to Appear, but there was immediately a Catching up of the Prey, as it were, out of the Mouth of the Lion, and with <hi>Violence</hi> pulling out
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97298:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:97298:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97298:18"/> of the Fire every One of the <hi>Saints</hi> below, and without the Loſs of One. In all which I deſire to be Clearly, Juſtly, and Candidly Underſtood.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is leſs Wonder, that the Wicked Captiv'd and Bound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Condemnation, and the <hi>Glory of the Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> for the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> ſhining juſt in their Faces, ſhould break out into that Outrage of <hi>Gog and Magog.</hi> For thus, as Dead all that Time, not in the Senſe of Suffering and Torment, but of any Spirit for Action againſt the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> They lay Bound and Fetter'd; It is no wonder then, that upon the withdrawing of the <hi>Glories of that Kingdom, Satan</hi> and that <hi>Gog and Magog</hi> break out into that Attempt, upon theſe Accounts;</p>
            <p n="1">1. All the Conviction and Puniſhment the <hi>Divels</hi> have been under theſe <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> and of the <hi>Damned</hi> throughout <hi>Eternity,</hi> does not according to the Judgment of all <hi>Divines</hi> upon <hi>Scripture,</hi> at all abate their <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> and <hi>Rage againſt God;</hi> but in what-ever they find their <hi>Chain</hi> looſe and allowing Liberty, They take it. This then will be the Caſe of <hi>Satan, Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> at the end of the <hi>Thouſand Years;</hi> They find the <hi>Chains</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> looſe about Them, ſo They Stir, They Move thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There is no doubt, <hi>Satan</hi> is the Name of the Higheſt <hi>Dominion, Power,</hi> and <hi>Influence</hi> of <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> in <hi>Scripture;</hi> He therefore being parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly <hi>looſed</hi> at the end of the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> mightily Agitates and Enflames to the Higheſt the <hi>Highly dispos'd Spirits</hi> of the <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> full of <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>Hatred</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Loſs</hi> and <hi>Torture</hi> of which They will have Endur'd a <hi>Thouſand Years;</hi> beſides the undoubted Foreſight of the <hi>Lake</hi> for ever; And not able ſo ſtrongly Chain'd, to have mov'd againſt it; upon a <hi>Looſening of Satan,</hi> and a <hi>Power of Action,</hi> as it were of ſome <hi>Livelineſs,</hi> by the <hi>Thouſand Years Glory</hi> Retiring; They are under <hi>Satan's Energy,</hi> call'd <hi>Deception</hi> becauſe of its <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſes,</hi> how Powerful ſoever; That they <hi>Gather,</hi> and <hi>Compaſs the Holy City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Wiſdom, Juſtice, Glory,</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in a Supream manner permitting, Order alſo, and over-rule this Effort.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there might be a full Diſplay of the <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>Irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable Spirits</hi> of <hi>Satan,</hi> and this <hi>loſt Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> of the <hi>Condemned,</hi> and of their <hi>Fittedneſs</hi> for the <hi>Wrath</hi> of <hi>Christ's</hi> Coming Down; not as a Second <hi>Conflagration</hi> of the <hi>New Heaven and Earth,</hi> which by a milder Exffection <hi>Fly away,</hi> when <hi>Chriſt Delivers up the Kingdom;</hi> but on <hi>Satan</hi> and his <hi>Hoſts,</hi> only <hi>Fire comes down,</hi> as it were, <hi>Hell</hi> from <hi>Heaven</hi> upon Them, ſhutting them up for ever <hi>in the Lake;</hi> where there ſhall be an <hi>utter Impoſſibility</hi> of <hi>Satan being Looſed,</hi> of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> Feeling any ſuch <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Action,</hi> or <hi>Gathering in Battel for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When therefore all the <hi>Numbers, Strength, utmost Efforts of Rage</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> in <hi>Satan</hi> and all his <hi>Legions</hi> and <hi>Hoſts</hi> are thus at the Heighth; there is then this Supream Manifeſtation of the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of God</hi> againſt theſe <hi>Armies,</hi> whoſe Number is as the <hi>Sand on the Sea;</hi> That the <hi>Grace, Love,</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> of <hi>God</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrist</hi> in the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:97298:18"/> 
               <hi>Caſtle, Camp,</hi> or <hi>Strong Citadel</hi> of his <hi>Saints</hi> in the <hi>New Earth,</hi> the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> below, the <hi>Beloved City,</hi> might be ſeen at laſt in this <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> and <hi>Glorious Deliverance</hi> and <hi>Reſcue.</hi> It is therefore call'd a <hi>Battel,</hi> even as the Second Part of that <hi>Great Battel of the Day of God Almighty</hi> at <hi>Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geddon;</hi> And now the <hi>Victory</hi> is <hi>Compleat</hi> and <hi>Irrecoverable,</hi> by the <hi>Catar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſis,</hi> or <hi>Caſting into the Lake,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t after a Full and Abſolute <hi>Judgment</hi> immediately followed; And of this <hi>Battel,</hi> even as of that of <hi>Armaged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> All the <hi>Great Battels, Deliverances,</hi> and <hi>Victories,</hi> as of <hi>Moſes</hi> over <hi>Amalek, Joſhua,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 18. <hi>Aſa, Hezekiah, Constantine, Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> his Laſt againſt <hi>Eugenius,</hi> and <hi>Argobaſtes,</hi> were <hi>Types.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. By way of <hi>Recollection,</hi> and for further <hi>Preparation</hi> concerning the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> let us conſider the Six-fold <hi>Repetition</hi> of the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> Rev. 20. and how they are Aſſign'd; which will add Certainty, and Luſtre to both the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> and the <hi>Hipotheſis,</hi> or <hi>Frame</hi> of <hi>Doctrine</hi> built upon them</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are Aſſign'd to the Binding of <hi>Satan,</hi> the <hi>Dragon,</hi> the Old <hi>Tempting,</hi> and <hi>Deceiving Serpent,</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Satan,</hi> the Great <hi>Accuſer</hi> and <hi>Adverſary;</hi> He was laid hold on by the <hi>Angel,</hi> or <hi>Miniſters of the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vine Power and Pleaſure,</hi> having the <hi>Key of that dark Vault of Impoſſibility</hi> for <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> to Appear or Act, but in the <hi>Torment</hi> of his own Guilty and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable <hi>Spir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t;</hi> as the <hi>Chain</hi> alſo Signifies; ſo much as in the ſmalleſt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> even as at all Times He is Remanded into it, and Held in it, but according to the Permiſſion of God; He was now <hi>laid Hold upon, Bound</hi> and <hi>Chain'd,</hi> and <hi>Seal'd up</hi> for a <hi>Thouſand Years.</hi> Here <hi>Satan</hi> is Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd as in the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>whole Hoſt of fallen wicked Spirits,</hi> full of <hi>Power, Might,</hi> and <hi>Rage,</hi> as well as <hi>Counſel</hi> and <hi>Policy;</hi> the whole <hi>Number of</hi> theſe <hi>Intelligences, Spirits</hi> and their <hi>Action,</hi> is as effectually, and to all Intents and Purpoſes <hi>Bound</hi> for the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> as it ſhall be, when <hi>Satan</hi> is <hi>Caſt into the Lake for Eternity,</hi> and under the <hi>Abſoluteneſs</hi> of <hi>Kingdome,</hi> when all <hi>Enemies ſubdued, God</hi> ſhall be <hi>All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are Aſſign'd to the <hi>Not deceiving the Nations,</hi> till thoſe <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are Expired or <hi>Finiſht.</hi> Now it is moſt Eviden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Theſe <hi>Nations</hi> are not the <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>Saved,</hi> Chap 21. 24. and Healed by the <hi>Leaves of the Tree of Life,</hi> Chap. 22. <hi>v.</hi> 3. For Theſe were De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed from <hi>Heaven;</hi> But there were at the ſame Time other <hi>Nations Saved,</hi> and <hi>Healed,</hi> a <hi>Holy and Beloved City.</hi> There is therefore a certain. Aſſurance, the <hi>Nations</hi> here ſpoken of, are the <hi>Wicked</hi> Reſerved to Future <hi>Deſtruction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Now Theſe, I ſay, are Really <hi>the Dead,</hi> who (as I ſhall juſt now ſpeak more) were <hi>Symbolized</hi> by <hi>Nations,</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> more properly <hi>Aliens,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> often ſignifies, <hi>from the Common-wealth of Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>New Jeruſalem below.</hi> But for the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> they are not to be ſtirr'd by <hi>Satan;</hi> They cannot be <hi>Deceiv'd</hi> into any Action againſt the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> The <hi>Glory of Chriſt's Kingdom</hi> is ſo Full in their <hi>Face,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are Aſſigned to the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and all the <hi>Saints</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:97298:19"/> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe <hi>Saintſhip</hi> is <hi>Symbolized</hi> by the <hi>Not worſhipping the Beaſt, &amp;c.</hi> That is, as <hi>Pure</hi> to <hi>God</hi> in all <hi>Ages before</hi> the <hi>Beast,</hi> and making up <hi>One Church of the First Born</hi> with Them; as the <hi>Apostle</hi> calls this whole Number of <hi>Saints:</hi> Theſe are Rais'd in Bodies of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>Reign with Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>Thouſand Years Kingdom,</hi> a Thouſand Years.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Theſe <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are Aſſigned to the <hi>Reſt of the Dead</hi> not <hi>Living again,</hi> till the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are <hi>Finiſht;</hi> And theſe <hi>Dead</hi> ſignifie to me Thoſe, Chap. 19. <hi>Slain with the Sword of Chriſt's Mouth;</hi> and on whoſe <hi>Fleſh</hi> the <hi>Fowls,</hi> viz. the <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>Christ Triumphing</hi> in the <hi>Vengeance,</hi> and <hi>Waſhing their Feet in the Blood of the Wicked,</hi> are <hi>Satisfied</hi> upon. It is Expreſly ſaid, <hi>They Lived Not,</hi> which is Principally to be underſtood of the <hi>Highest of Life in the Higheſt Senſes of it;</hi> For as ſoon as ever <hi>The Saints were Rais'd,</hi> All the <hi>Wicked Dead</hi> were Rais'd; But <hi>They Lived</hi> not, <hi>Living</hi> not ſo, as to <hi>Reign with Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Dead Saints Rais'd, Saints of the Firſt Reſurrection liv<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe They are of a <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> though a <hi>Reſurrection of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt,</hi> and to <hi>Condemnation;</hi> Therefore They are ſpoken of next to the <hi>Raiſed Saints:</hi> But They <hi>Lived not,</hi> till the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> were Expir'd; As ſoon as ever that is ſaid, it is Added immediately, <hi>This is the Firſt Reſurrection;</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Onely Reſurrection</hi> to <hi>Living:</hi> But Theſe <hi>Dead</hi> were not of it, and ſo They never can <hi>Live</hi> in the true Senſes of <hi>Life,</hi> though <hi>Rais'd;</hi> For They <hi>Liv'd</hi> not till the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection</hi> were <hi>Finiſht,</hi> and ſo could not ſo much as <hi>Taſte</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> or <hi>Partake</hi> of it; and then They never can; For they are immediately Forepriz'd; as ſoon as ever it had been ſaid, They were the <hi>Dead,</hi> who for the <hi>Thouſand Years Liv'd not;</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed and Holy is He that is Partaker of the Firſt Reſurrection, over ſuch the Second Death hath no power;</hi> Over All elſe it hath: The <hi>Dead</hi> therefore, which Theſe are, are <hi>Caſt into the Lake of the Second Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There may be alſo a Secondary Senſe of the <hi>Dead not living,</hi> viz. Not <hi>Appearing,</hi> as <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>og,</hi> till the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are <hi>Finiſht,</hi> as hath been ſhewn; But This is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Principal.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Theſe <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are Aſſign'd to the <hi>Partakers</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Holy Saints,</hi> and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> State of <hi>Paradiſe-Bleſſedneſs,</hi> making up with the <hi>Riſen Saints; We All;</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 25. and 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 17. viz. <hi>who Come to us, and make us up</hi> to an <hi>All,</hi> to a Complement of <hi>Saints,</hi> who cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the <hi>Dead;</hi> for They <hi>Die not All,</hi> but are <hi>Chang'd,</hi> and ſo <hi>Participants</hi> of the <hi>First Reſurrection;</hi> Not the <hi>Dead,</hi> for They are the <hi>Living,</hi> and <hi>Remaining:</hi> Theſe alſo, though they are not <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>Firſt R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrection,</hi> yet <hi>Partakers;</hi> Though they are not ſaid here to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive,</hi> yet They are <hi>Prieſts of God</hi> and of <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>Reign with Him as Kings of the Earth; Nations Saved, and Healed a Thouſand Years;</hi> And ſo the <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of the <hi>Redemption of Chriſt</hi> Abounds in the Sight of their ſhort Danger; and They are <hi>Caught up to Chriſt,</hi> and to all the <hi>Saints above,</hi> and are <hi>ever</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97298:19"/> 
               <hi>with the Lord,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Second Death</hi> hath no <hi>Power over Them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Theſe <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are Aſſign'd not in their whole <hi>Line,</hi> but in their end, to the <hi>Looſing of Satan</hi> for that <hi>little ſpace;</hi> to the <hi>Inſurrection</hi> of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> againſt the <hi>Holy City;</hi> and the <hi>Caſting Satan</hi> and the <hi>Dead</hi> into the <hi>Lake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If it ſhould be ſaid, How can One and the Same ſort of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be <hi>Known</hi> to be the ſame, when <hi>Prophecy</hi> hath ſo varied their <hi>Names,</hi> Calling Them the <hi>Nations,</hi> or <hi>Gentiles;</hi> The <hi>Dead; Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> So Great a <hi>Prophecy</hi> as This of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd a <hi>Bleſſedneſs upon Them who Read, and who Hear it,</hi> Expects, All ſhould be moſt <hi>Accurate</hi> and <hi>Diligent</hi> in Comparing it Self with it Self, bringing All <hi>Scripture</hi> into a Compare with it, that ſo the <hi>Two Leaved Gates of its Truth may open to Them,</hi> and the <hi>Secret Treaſures,</hi> even <hi>Treaſures of Darkneſs,</hi> as it ſeems to our dim Underſtanding, may be <hi>Diſclos'd</hi> to Them; And if Any think the Trouble too Great, <hi>They are ſhut Out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Caſe therefore by Comparing, we come to underſtand, that there is not only fair Inducement to think <hi>the Dead, the Nations, Gog and Magog,</hi> to be the ſame, but Greateſt Aſſurance, They muſt be the ſame.</p>
            <p>There is fair Inducement, in that <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> being Deſcribed as a <hi>Great Multitude, whoſe Number is as the Sand of the Sea;</hi> They muſt be a Collection of <hi>Nations,</hi> and therefore They are expreſly call'd the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> Chap. 9. <hi>v.</hi> 8. and a <hi>Hammonah of Nations,</hi> as of Old in the <hi>Type, Ezek.</hi> 39 9. Now we find ſuch a <hi>Collection of Nations, Slain with the Sword of Chriſt's Mouth,</hi> Chap. 19. For <hi>v.</hi> 18. Their <hi>Fleſh</hi> is Expos'd as a <hi>Feaſt</hi> to the <hi>Fowls</hi> in ſuch a Collection of <hi>Kings, Captains, Small and Great;</hi> And <hi>v:</hi> 19. They are ſaid to be the <hi>Kings of the Earth,</hi> and their <hi>Armies Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together under the Beaſt,</hi> as their Chief; And when the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> were <hi>Taken and thrown into the Lake,</hi> verſe 20. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Reſt,</hi> even the <hi>whole Reſt</hi> beſides the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> are <hi>v.</hi> 21. expreſly ſaid to be <hi>Slain with the Sword of Chriſt's Mouth;</hi> And ſo They became the <hi>Dead;</hi> therefore Chap. 20. They are call'd very properly in ſo Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour a Context, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Reſt of the Dead;</hi> by the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of Chap. 19. <hi>v.</hi> 21. and the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, put together; <hi>The Remnant ſlain,</hi> Chap. 19. 21. <hi>The Remnant of the Dead, c.</hi> 20. 5. <hi>Slain</hi> and <hi>Dead</hi> being moſt Conjoyn'd in Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, They appear to be the ſame: And theſe <hi>Reſt ſlain,</hi> and ſo <hi>Dead,</hi> are in their whole Number and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ollection, the <hi>Gog and Magog ſo gathered together,</hi> as to the <hi>Firſt Battel</hi> at <hi>Armageddon</hi> So to the <hi>Laſt Battel of the Thouſand Years,</hi> or of the <hi>Day of Judgment ending.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is beyond this Indu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ement, ſtrong Argument; For who-ever Live in the State of the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> muſt be <hi>Partakers of the Firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection;</hi> Becauſe They are the <hi>Nations of the Saved, ſaved from the Sword of Him that Sate on the Horſe;</hi> As they are call'd, <hi>The Land brought back,</hi> or <hi>Reſcued from the Sword, Ezek.</hi> 38. 8. All Thoſe are <hi>Healed with the Leaves of the Tree of Life;</hi> They muſt be therefore the <hi>Living,</hi> for All that are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97298:20"/> 
               <hi>Living</hi> are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the very <hi>Left</hi> as under a peculiar Guard, and Care of Life; So They are call'd the <hi>People left,</hi> and <hi>Eſcaped,</hi> and the <hi>Living, Eſay</hi> 4. 2, 3. and by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> compar'd to <hi>Fiſhes</hi> in the <hi>Living,</hi> and <hi>Healing Waters;</hi> wherein whatever doth <hi>Live,</hi> ſhall <hi>Live;</hi> and the <hi>Dead, viz.</hi> the <hi>Raiſed-condemn'd,</hi> to <hi>Mariſhes,</hi> or <hi>Miry places,</hi> not <hi>Healed,</hi> but <hi>Given to Salt, Ezek.</hi> 47. 9, 11. even the <hi>Salt of that Fire, never Quench'd, March</hi> 9. 47. From whence it Follows, whoever <hi>Eſcape in that Great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation,</hi> the <hi>Fire,</hi> the <hi>Sword,</hi> the <hi>Hail</hi> of the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly Men</hi> at that <hi>Battle of Armageddon,</hi> are the <hi>Living Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Written in the Book of Life,</hi> and <hi>ſhall Live;</hi> And All other are to be Accounted the <hi>Dead,</hi> Firſt <hi>Slain with the Sword of Chriſt's Mouth,</hi> punniſh'd with <hi>Everlasting Deſtruction,</hi> and then <hi>cast into the Lake</hi> at laſt: For ſo it is <hi>Everlaſting Deſtruction</hi> to be <hi>Slain with the Sword of Chriſt's Mouth,</hi> Becauſe All the ſo <hi>Slain</hi> are the <hi>Dead,</hi> not <hi>Partakers</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurection;</hi> So the <hi>Second Death</hi> gets the <hi>Power</hi> over Them, certainly and infallibly; They are <hi>cast into the Lake</hi> that <hi>Burns with Fire,</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> which is the <hi>Second Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus far Pre-caution'd concerning all Things relating to the State of the 1000 Years, and the <hi>Little Space of Sathan's Looſing</hi> after the 1000 Years: I will now in very Brief, Lay down ſome very ſhort Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Clearing the Doubts Ariſing from the State of the <hi>Living Remaining Saints,</hi> as It is <hi>Symboliz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d,</hi> and Figur'd by the <hi>Church of Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſit.</hi> 1. The Great Reaſon perſwading, The <hi>Church of Laodicea</hi> is the Repreſentation of the <hi>Saints</hi> after the 1000 Years, is, that, There are Great Reaſons to be Given, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſewhere declar'd; That the <hi>Seven Churches</hi> are as a <hi>Prophetic Seheme,</hi> prepar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d by Chriſt to Run the whole Line of Time, Allotted to the <hi>Apocalyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic Prophecy;</hi> as it is firſt Given by thoſe <hi>Churches,</hi> with Relation to the <hi>Church of Christ,</hi> to the very end of All at the <hi>Kingdom deliver'd up;</hi> and as more Generally, It is the Second Time, Fully Given in the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Book, ſealed</hi> with <hi>Seven Seals,</hi> and Gradually <hi>Open'd</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 2 If it be ſo, Then the <hi>Philadelphian Church</hi> being the <hi>Church,</hi> on which the <hi>Thouſand-Years-New-Jeruſalem comes down,</hi> and Reſts, The <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicean Church</hi> that comes after it, muſt needs be the State of the <hi>Church</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Glories of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> above being withdrawn, <hi>Sathan Looſed,</hi> and the Aſſault by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog, deceiv'd</hi> by Him, preparing; For All Theſe Immediately ſucceed the 1000 Years, if then, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> Agrees in Time with the 1000 Y. and deſcribes the State of the <hi>Church</hi> during thoſe 1000 Years, the <hi>Church,</hi> that Follows that, muſt deſcribe the State of the <hi>Church</hi> after the 1000 Years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſit.</hi> 3. There is a wonderful Agreement hereunto of the Titles of Chriſt in writing to this <hi>Church, viz.</hi> the <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Faithful Witneſs</hi> to the Laſt End; about to Cloſe the whole Created State, by <hi>delivering</hi> up the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> as well as the <hi>Beginning of the Creation of God;</hi> the Name of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97298:20"/> 
               <hi>Church, Laodicea,</hi> as in a Judiciary Power over the <hi>Nations</hi> of the Raiſed, Condemn'd Wicked, Lying Captive at Chriſt's <hi>Feet,</hi> and ſo at his <hi>Saints Feet,</hi> as the <hi>Dead.</hi> The Promiſe of <hi>Sitting down</hi> with Chriſt on his <hi>Throne,</hi> (They being <hi>Caught</hi> up to it;) and that, as Chriſt <hi>Sat down</hi> on his <hi>Father's Throne,</hi> till the Time of his own <hi>Kingdom,</hi> So theſe <hi>Saints ſit,</hi> while the Laſt Act of Judgment on <hi>Sathan, Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> on <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> is in Sentence and Execution, and ſo until the <hi>Kingdom deliver'd</hi> up; All theſe I ſay, Admirably Agree to the Laſt End of Things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſit.</hi> 4. The ſeveral Branches of the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> muſt not be Rigorouſly Applied to the <hi>Saints Living, Remaining</hi> in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> State, but carried only to the Principal Scope; and what-ever Exceeds that, muſt be underſtood, as in all Parables of <hi>Scripture,</hi> to Flouriſh and Embelliſh the Figures, that They may moſt to the Life, Expreſs that Principal Scope; and the Reſt muſt vale off, and be Applied only to the Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work it ſelf of the <hi>Figure;</hi> as here It muſt to the <hi>Church of Laodicea,</hi> that was in Being, when the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> was written; and ſo Theſe Following Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars are of Chief Remark, in which, let us then <hi>Hear,</hi> what the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> thus ſpeaks to the Church of <hi>Laodicea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lukewarmneſs of the <hi>Church of Laodicea,</hi> Applied to the <hi>Living Remaining Saints</hi> cannot be underſtood, but of the abatement of the fervors for the <hi>Glory of the Jeruſalem above,</hi> to which hitherto theſe <hi>Kings of the Earth,</hi> the <hi>Saints below</hi> had <hi>Brought their Glory:</hi> But now thoſe <hi>Glories</hi> from Above being withdrawn, and the ſo Free and Illuſtrious Communications cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, Theſe <hi>Saints</hi> below, whereas They rather Acquieſce in their State below, at leaſt, as very well; ſhould have Burnt in an Immediate <hi>Zeal</hi> to be <hi>Caught</hi> up, as <hi>Elijah</hi> in <hi>Charriots of Fire</hi> to Chriſt above, and to be ever with Him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Spewing</hi> out of <hi>Chriſt's Mouth</hi> can by no means indeed be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of a diſgraceful, diſhonourable End put by Chriſt to his own <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> below, or on his, the <hi>Living Remaining Saints;</hi> but only that ſeeing a Church State on <hi>Earth,</hi> Born up in <hi>Glory</hi> from the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> State above, during the 1000 Years, could by the decree of God, Aſſigning only a 1000 Years for it, be no longer; and that his <hi>Saints</hi> not yet veſted in <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality,</hi> and <hi>Incorruption,</hi> would be liable to <hi>Sathan</hi>'s Aſſaults, and to Temptation, and to Fall from their Glory; He would therefore <hi>Spew</hi> out for ever Any Church-State, but what ſhould be Fix<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d in <hi>Immortality</hi> and <hi>Incorruption,</hi> and ſo Immediately be <hi>deliver'd</hi> up through Himſelf to <hi>God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and the <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Spewing,</hi> or <hi>Vomiting out of Chriſt's Mouth,</hi> ſignifies then the utter Impoſſibility for ever of any Lapſible Church State, or what is not ſo E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally ſecur'd; Seeing it is moſt Impoſſible, Chriſt ſhould <hi>Return to his Vomit</hi> any more.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Church of <hi>Laodiceas,</hi> ſo high Account of it ſelf, as being <hi>Rich,</hi> and Increas'd with Goods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but in Chriſt's Account being <hi>Poor, Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ble, Blind,</hi> and <hi>Naked,</hi> and <hi>Counſell'd</hi> therefore by Him, to <hi>Buy of Him</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:97298:21"/> 
               <hi>Gold tryed in the Fire, white Rayment, and Eye-Salve<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as Applied to the <hi>Living Remaining Saints,</hi> is no otherwiſe to be underſtood; then that <hi>All that Excellent State</hi> of the <hi>Jeruſalem below,</hi> was through the <hi>Beams of a free Communication</hi> from the <hi>Jerulalem above,</hi> with which It was in Union; but that being no longer poſſible becauſe the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> were <hi>finiſht,</hi> there could be no Satisfaction in any longer Continuance below, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever They might be Tempted to miſtake concerning it; For the State of the <hi>Church</hi> ſo Deſerted was <hi>poor, miſerable, blind, naked;</hi> and the Good State could no way be Recover'd, but by the <hi>Pure Gold,</hi> the <hi>White Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Eye-Salve of Immortality, Incorru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion,</hi> and <hi>Immediate Sight of Chriſt Face to Face,</hi> in his <hi>Kingdom above.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. By the <hi>Rebuke</hi> and <hi>Chaſtiſement</hi> on <hi>Laodicea,</hi> as It may be Apply'd to the <hi>Living Remaining Saints,</hi> is Figur'd, in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Compaſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng</hi> the <hi>Camp</hi> or the <hi>Munition</hi> of the <hi>Saints, Christ's</hi> main Intention and Deſign which was <hi>Love;</hi> the end of it being to ſtir up that <hi>Zeal,</hi> and <hi>change of Mind,</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipiſcency,</hi> producing an Earneſtneſs to be <hi>Caught up to Christ</hi> in his <hi>Kingdom above;</hi> according to the Neceſſity that muſt needs A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pear from ſo Bold an Attempt of <hi>Satan,</hi> as ſoon as ever the <hi>Glories</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem above</hi> were ſtay'd, which was the Security of that <hi>below;</hi> And ſeeing there was but a <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> Determined to that Univerſal Glory of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and there could be no longer ſuch a <hi>Communication,</hi> and yet that there was not that Ardor in theſe <hi>Saints</hi> to be Tranſlated to the High<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt State; <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtops alſo thoſe <hi>Influences,</hi> that Fetter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d <hi>Satan,</hi> and the <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> which They immediately Feel as a <hi>Looſening of Themſelves,</hi> and ſo They <hi>Come up,</hi> and <hi>Cover the New Earth,</hi> and <hi>Compaſs the City;</hi> So that the <hi>Remove of the Saints</hi> is, as by a violent Motion, as it were <hi>Spew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out;</hi> and by a Severe Admonition upon the <hi>Saints,</hi> that Their <hi>Zeal</hi> for that <hi>Remove up,</hi> might <hi>Flame out,</hi> and ſo <hi>Chriſt in a Zeal of Fire from Heaven, Devouring their Enemies,</hi> might Reſcue Them: This <hi>Tranſlation</hi> is therefore call'd <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 17. Implying a <hi>Violence in the whole Tranſaction;</hi> as of a <hi>mighty Reſcue from a deſtroying Beaſt of Prey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Chriſt Standing</hi> ſo Graciouſly at the <hi>Door,</hi> and <hi>Knocking,</hi> even at every <hi>Door,</hi> and Aſſuring his <hi>Free Communion</hi> in <hi>Supping with his Saints,</hi> and <hi>They</hi> with <hi>Him,</hi> ſhews in the Application to the <hi>Living Remaining Saints,</hi> that Never-failing <hi>Love of Chriſt, as</hi> the <hi>Redeemer</hi> and <hi>Second Adam;</hi> that when thoſe <hi>Brighter Rays</hi> were Retracted and with held; yet would not Fail to Viſit Them, by no leſs Effectual, though not by ſo <hi>Resplendent Rays;</hi> and when <hi>He</hi> did not Viſit Them, as a <hi>New Jeruſalem below,</hi> any longer to Continue; <hi>He</hi> yet lookt with a particular Care and Love to every Single <hi>Saint,</hi> to <hi>Looſe</hi> not ſo much as One; not One of thoſe <hi>Saved,</hi> and continually <hi>Healed</hi> with the <hi>Leaves of the Tree of Life,</hi> and the <hi>Water of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife,</hi> being poſſible to be <hi>Loſt:</hi> Foraſmuch as not One was a <hi>Son of Death,</hi> for that were to be a <hi>Son of Perdition,</hi> and of the <hi>Second Death,</hi> and ſo not to be of the <hi>Saved</hi> of the <hi>Nations,</hi> nor of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> over whom the <hi>Second Death can have no power.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97298:21"/>
            <p n="6"> 6. Theſe <hi>Living Remaining Saints</hi> are therefore every One <hi>Over-commers,</hi> and ſo every One <hi>Caught up</hi> to Sit with <hi>Chriſt</hi> on his <hi>Throne,</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> Sate down on the <hi>Father's Throne;</hi> They Sit with Him in thoſe Great Acts of <hi>Judgment,</hi> and when <hi>Satan is Caſt into the Lake;</hi> And when <hi>Death, Hell,</hi> and the <hi>Dead,</hi> are Caſt into the <hi>Lake,</hi> the Great and Final Acts of <hi>Judgment,</hi> They put on <hi>Immortality</hi> and <hi>Incorruption:</hi> They with all <hi>Saints</hi> meet <hi>Chriſt</hi> in that High Act of Reſignation of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and having been <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> before, during all the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> are in one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Perfected into an Equality to the <hi>Saints of the Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> and So to <hi>Angels,</hi> to whom Thoſe are <hi>Equal</hi> at that <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> that Poſſibility of Dying and Falling, of which for the Glory of the Redeemer, and his Grace, and Mighty Power over <hi>Satan</hi> and the <hi>Dead,</hi> there was but a Shew and no more, even all <hi>Mortality is ſwallow'd up of Life,</hi> and ſo They are <hi>Ever with the Lord,</hi> who is <hi>Ever with the Father All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus <hi>I</hi> have according to the <hi>utmoſt Grace</hi> and <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> God hath herein been pleas'd to give me, Set out the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> which is indeed the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> and there is no <hi>Second;</hi> All <hi>Second</hi> to it, is <hi>Second Death;</hi> as <hi>I</hi> have and do Affirm Conſtantly. All <hi>Saints</hi> are either <hi>Principals</hi> or <hi>Partakers;</hi> Here are the <hi>Two</hi> in <hi>Capital Letters</hi> written <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 5. 14. <hi>This is the FIRST RES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RRECTION. This is the SECOND DEATH.</hi> So that (however it be not Intentional, not Underſtood by Them that ſay it,) To ſay, the <hi>Thouſand Years are paſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready;</hi> Is to ſay, <hi>The Reſurrection is paſt already,</hi> as <hi>I</hi> have already Obſerv'd.</p>
            <p>And if They are paſt already, how comes it to paſs the <hi>Seaſon</hi> ſince their Ending, hath been not a <hi>Little Seaſon?</hi> as the <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſo Poſitively Aſſerts it to be: For Beginning the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> at <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and Ending Them at 1300, when the <hi>Turkiſh Euphrates</hi> Began to Swell over in the World, there muſt have paſs'd about 400 Years ſince, which Compar'd with a <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> beſides what ſtill may be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, it is no <hi>Small Seaſon;</hi> Nor does <hi>Prophecy</hi> barely ſay, <hi>The ſeaſon of Satan's Looſing</hi> is <hi>Small</hi> or <hi>Little;</hi> But it Deſcribes <hi>All Things</hi> in the moſt Rapid Motion to a Final End; Which will by no means Agree with ſo long a Time, as hath already Actually paſs'd: But thus it Fares with All, who will Deny <hi>Great Scripture Evidence;</hi> They are forc'd to <hi>ſwallow Camels of Difficulty,</hi> for the <hi>Gnats</hi> they ſo <hi>ſtrain at.</hi> But God forbid <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſeem to Charge All that do it with <hi>Hipocriſie;</hi> except that <hi>ſecret Hipocriſie</hi> Remaining and Lurking in the Heart of the Holieſt here: Nor do, or can <hi>I</hi> in the leaſt ſuſpect the leaſt Shadow of any Favour to the <hi>Horrid Anticriſtianiſms of Popery,</hi> in the ſudden Reſolve to be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> if one <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Angel,</hi> or <hi>Governour</hi> over all the <hi>Chriſtian Churches</hi> could be ſuppos'd to be the <hi>Inſtitution of Chriſt:</hi> For certainly if ſuch a Love of Pre-eminence had not been Curſed by God, as making Preparation for <hi>the Man of Sin,</hi> to <hi>ſit ſo High in the Temple of God,</hi> and to let into it the <hi>Deſolating Abomination;</hi> That might have been the moſt pardonable Errour in <hi>Popery;</hi> Eſpecially according to even <hi>Proteſtant Epiſcopal Principles:</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:97298:22"/> For They beginning at <hi>Deacons,</hi> (as the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Firſt <hi>Degree</hi> that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> intended) go up to <hi>Prieſts,</hi> from <hi>Prieſts</hi> to <hi>Archdeacons</hi> or <hi>Deans,</hi> from them to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> from <hi>Biſhops</hi> to <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> and why not to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs,</hi> as Primitive? And why not from thence, (as All Heighth would Culminate to One) to the <hi>Pope,</hi> as the <hi>Head of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> the <hi>Vicar of Christ,</hi> the <hi>Succeſſor of Saint Peter,</hi> who is Nam'd, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as if a <hi>Scandal</hi> were laid into that <hi>Philoprotenſia,</hi> if <hi>I</hi> may ſo call it, that <hi>Primating Affectation;</hi> But All Sincere <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> though moſt <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> Abhor the Dreadful Conſequences from ſuch a <hi>Primacy,</hi> as the <hi>Papaoy</hi> Claims; not only over Conſciences, but over Princes, and Civil Powers, in <hi>Ordine ad Spiritualia,</hi> or to Infamous Ends, call'd <hi>Spiritual;</hi> which <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality,</hi> I am very prone to ſuſpect, was Foretold in the <hi>Holy Spirit's Choice</hi> of that Word [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 8. and that it does not only ſignifie, <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, viz. Myſtically,</hi> but is alſo <hi>Prophetick</hi> of that Great uſe <hi>Anticbriſt</hi> ſhould make of that Word <hi>[Spiritual;]</hi> On which Account I cannot but pray, All <hi>Proteſtants</hi> might get from under the Fathality of that Word, any way Secularly Apply'd; as alſo from any <hi>Primacy</hi> Allied to the <hi>Feet of Clay;</hi> I have ſo Great an Honour, and Love for many, who ſtand ſo high in, as They are call'd, <hi>Spiritual Dignities,</hi> who, I am Bound to hope, are yet in their Truly Chief Scituation, <hi>Stars in the Right Hand of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Chief Reaſon I make this Digreſſion, is, that I may obſerve, how far One may be from ſuch Portentous Conſequences, that may ſeem yet to have ſome Ground; Such are charg'd on me on Dr. <hi>Criſps</hi> Account; All which I deteſt with Greateſt deteſtation, as I Fully Believe he did, but minded only to Give the Full Conſolation to Conſciences Ariſing from Chriſt, being an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Ranſom</hi> in our Steed, a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> a <hi>Surety,</hi> and <hi>Sin</hi> for us; and deſigning All his diſcourſes of Theſe Things to be Confin'd to the <hi>Elect</hi> only, who ſhall All be brought in by Chriſt, and Receive an Efficacious <hi>Spirit of Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to Return to the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> have Affirm'd to be the <hi>Perfection of Time;</hi> Becauſe It is the <hi>Fulneſs of Times,</hi> or of <hi>All Times,</hi> to which the <hi>Scripture</hi> therefore Sets up as <hi>Pillars,</hi> Two <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>It is Done, It is Done;</hi> One of Deſtruction to the <hi>Wicked,</hi> One of <hi>Salvation</hi> to the <hi>Saints:</hi> Therefore <hi>I</hi> Avouch a <hi>Scripture Line of Time</hi> from the <hi>Firſt Sabbath,</hi> to this <hi>Great Sabbatiſm</hi> in Expreſs, either <hi>Hiſtorick firſt,</hi> or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Prophetick number'd Nambers;</hi> And becauſe This is a <hi>Divine Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> It is not ſubject to the endleſs Contraſts and Feuds of Greateſt <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologers,</hi> never to be Reconciled by Perſons of Greateſt <hi>Learning, Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>Judgment;</hi> much leſs by Me leſs than the leaſt of the <hi>Sons of Learning,</hi> not Worthy to be Nam'd among Them; Yet by the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> in this Matter <hi>I Am, what I Am,</hi> and hold in my Hand the Uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Clew of His Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Some ſmall <hi>Errata,</hi> The underſtanding Reader will pardon and mend. I only note page 9. line 16. for Believ'd, read, Beloved, p. 13. l. 24. for pro. read premiſes, p. 28. l. 35. for Effec. Read Affection, p. 29. l. 30. read, that, before Kingdom.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:97298:22"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT TO THE READER, <hi>Concerning the Thouſand Years, further Cleared.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInce the Finiſhing of the Fore-going Diſcourſe, as I was in Earneſt Thought about the Clearing the Due Aſſignation of the <hi>Thouſand Years;</hi> To the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection Reigning with Chriſt;</hi> To the <hi>Wicked Raiſed,</hi> but not <hi>Reigning with Chriſt,</hi> and ſo not <hi>Living;</hi> And to the <hi>Saints,</hi> the <hi>Living</hi> and the <hi>Remaining,</hi> or <hi>Left</hi> under a <hi>Guard of Life,</hi> Secur'd from the <hi>Sword of Him that Sat on the Horſe,</hi> and ſo <hi>never Dying.</hi> To every of which <hi>Claſſes,</hi> the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are plainly, and without any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in the Threefold mention of the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> Verſ. 4, 5, 6. Aſſign'd: It yet ſeem'd a Doubt to Me Worthy of a further <hi>Illuſtration,</hi> Where the univerſality of the <hi>Raiſed Saints;</hi> Concerning which, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is ſo clear, That <hi>Chriſt brings Them with Him,</hi> ſhould be plac'd: Becauſe They could not with ſuch Satisfaction be Repos'd either with the <hi>Martyrs</hi> and <hi>Non-Worſhippers</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt, &amp;c.</hi> Nor with the <hi>Partakers</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection,</hi> who, though <hi>Chang'd,</hi> are not <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aught up</hi> till a <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> after, which I never yet ſee Diſprov'd: Although becauſe <hi>Scripture</hi> is ſo <hi>Poſitive,</hi> All the <hi>Dead in Chriſt riſe firſt;</hi> They muſt have been Included in One of thoſe Two. And I did accordingly in the foregoing <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> Incline to place Them among the <hi>Martyrs, page</hi> 30. <hi>line</hi> 1. But yet a Deſire of a further Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation, remain'd with me; And, I hope, I may ſay, without vanity, <hi>God hath helped me.</hi> And I Found Their Seat is diſtinct, and in the Firſt Place, <hi>viz.</hi> In thoſe words, <hi>I ſaw Thrones</hi> and <hi>They Sate upon them,</hi> and <hi>Judgment was given to Them;</hi> moſt Agreeable with <hi>Daniel's Prophecy.</hi> Chap. 7. <hi>v.</hi> 26, 27. Who therefore are the <hi>They who Sate on Thrones?</hi> I know it may be ſaid, No More was meant, but that the <hi>Thrones</hi> were <hi>Sat upon,</hi> as, <hi>They ſhall require thy Soul,</hi> Luke 12. 20. and <hi>They may Receive You,</hi> Chap. 86. <hi>v.</hi> 9. But conſidering the following words, <hi>Judgment was given to Them;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:97298:23"/> cannot be thus any fair way Expounded. I conclude, The <hi>[They]</hi> muſt Relate to ſome Perſons ſpoken of before, and who ſhould They be, but <hi>Thoſe</hi> Signified by the <hi>Armies of Heaven,</hi> Chap. 19 14. who <hi>Followed Chriſt on white Horſes,</hi> in <hi>Linnen white and clean?</hi> Moſt Admirably Agreeing with the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Zechary; The Lord my God will come,</hi> and All <hi>Thy Saints with Thee,</hi> Zech. 14, 5: With the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4. 14. <hi>Thoſe that Sleep in Jeſus,</hi> will <hi>God b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing with Him;</hi> With the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of <hi>Jude,</hi> Reciting <hi>Enoch</hi>'s <hi>Prophecy,</hi> v. 14. <hi>The Lord cometh with Ten Thouſand of his Saints, &amp;c.</hi> Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n therefore the <hi>Prophecy</hi> had Diſpoſed of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſeveral Enemies of Chriſt; as the <hi>Beast,</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> Chap. 19. <hi>Cast into ehe Lake,</hi> and the <hi>Remnant Slain with the Sword of Chriſt's Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th,</hi> and <hi>Satan</hi> the <hi>Dragon Bound, &amp;c.</hi> Then it gives Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Armies of Heaven,</hi> that were with Chriſt in this Victorious Diſpoſe; And of <hi>Them,</hi> It ſays, <hi>I Saw Thron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>They</hi> [Thoſe Armies] <hi>Sate upon them,</hi> and <hi>Judgment was given to Them;</hi> And ſo being in the <hi>Fore-Front,</hi> or Firſt, <hi>Set on the Thrones,</hi> muſt needs <hi>Reign with Christ</hi> the <hi>Thouſand Years.</hi> Allowing therefore not only the <hi>Scripture-way</hi> of giving Account of Things, not in ſuch a Method as Humane Writings obſerve, and much more allowing for the Secrecy of <hi>Prophecy;</hi> This is to Me a Full Satisfactory Account, and I hope it will not be unworthy the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of All, who are Serious Conſiderers of theſe Things,</p>
            <p>Then follows the Account of All Suffering for the <hi>Witneſs of Jeſus,</hi> and for the <hi>Word of God;</hi> Surely from the Beginning of the World; but with an eſpecial Reference to the <hi>Roman</hi> way of Puniſhment of ſuch Offender<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſhewing a Direct Eye upon <hi>Roman-Martyrdoms,</hi> by <hi>Beheading;</hi> as <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> ſaid to be; But moſt particularly the <hi>Non-Worſhippers</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> who are ſo particularly Recorded for Three Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe hereby the <hi>Judgment</hi> upon Them as <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Rebels</hi> to the Government of Chriſt, as <hi>Antichriſt</hi> pretended, is as an Attainder by an Illegal Power, Signally taken off.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Prophecy</hi> all along before Inſiſting upon the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> his <hi>Image, &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> might have the Due Honour given to it, by placing a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Remark upon the Principal Subjects of it; So that it is moſt Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how any Rational Conſiderer of the <hi>Prophecy,</hi> can ſuppoſe <hi>Pagan Rome,</hi> Falling about 300 Years after <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Reſurrection,</hi> ſhould Take up ſuch a <hi>Prophecy,</hi> againſt ſo manifeſt Aſſurances, that it muſt Run on to the <hi>End of the World;</hi> That even the Wiſeſt <hi>Papist</hi> cannot Deny it: But what Violence muſt They uſe to it, that Believe the <hi>Papacy</hi> to be the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and yet ſo begin the <hi>Thouſand Years;</hi> That they muſt be long ago before Him <hi>Finiſh'd?</hi> Could ſuch a Prejudice be brought from this <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> or <hi>Scripture</hi> in general againſt my Doctrine of the <hi>Thouſand Years Kingdom,</hi> or ſuch a Proof againſt me, as I have given, of the <hi>Flying away,</hi> Revel. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Of the <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth;</hi> I would be ſo Retracting indeed, as Immediately to Retract, and even to Recant; In the mean Time, as I have Stated Things, I fear no Acceſſions to <hi>Mahomet</hi> by My Doctrine of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
